Everyone, so I wanted to make this video for a while. It is a comprehensive but general audience introduction to large language models like ChatGPT.
And what I'm hoping to achieve in this video is to give you kind of mental models for thinking through what it is that this tool is.
It is obviously magical and amazing in some respects. It's really good at some things, not very good at other things, and there's also a lot of sharp edges to be aware of.
So what is behind this text box?
You can put anything in there and press enter.
But what should you be putting there?
And what are these words generated back?
How does this work and what are you talking to exactly?
So I'm hoping to get at all those topics in this video.
We're going to go through the entire pipeline
of how this stuff is built, but I'm
going to keep everything sort of accessible
to a general audience.
So let's take a look at first how
you build something like Chatchy PT.
And along the way, I'm going to talk about some of the cognitive
the psychological implications of these tools.
Okay, so let's go to the chat GPT.
So there's going to be multiple stages arranged sequentially.
The first stage is called the pre-training stage.
And the first step of the pre-training stage
is to download and process the internet.
Now to get a sense of what this roughly looks like,
I recommend looking at this URL here.
So this company called Hugging Face collected
and created this data set called FindWeb.
And they go into a lot of detail on this blog post
on how they constructed the fine web data set.
And all of the major LLM providers
like OpenAI, Anthropic, and Google, and so on
will have some equivalent internally
of something like the fine web data set.
So roughly what are we trying to achieve here?
We're trying to get a ton of text from the internet,
from publicly available sources.
So we're trying to have a huge quantity
of very high quality documents.
And we also want very large diversity of documents
because we want to have a lot of knowledge inside these models.
So we want large diversity of high quality documents
and we want many, many of them.
And achieving this is quite complicated.
And as you can see here, it takes multiple stages to do well.
So let's take a look at what some of these stages look like in a bit.
For now, we'd like to just like to note that, for example, the fine web data set,
which is fairly representative, what you would see in a production-grade application,
actually ends up being only about 44 terabytes of disk space.
You can get a USB stick for like a terabyte very easily.
Or I think this could fit on a single hard drive
almost today.
So this is not a huge amount of data at the end of the day.
Even though the internet is very, very large,
we're working with text and we're also
filtering it aggressively.
So we end up with about 44 terabytes in this example.
So let's take a look at what this data looks like
and what some of these stages also are.
So the starting point for a lot of these efforts
and something that contributes most of the data
by the end of it, is data from CommonCroll.
So CommonCroll is an organization
that has been basically scouring the internet since 2007.
So as of 2024, for example, CommonCroll has indexed
2.7 billion web pages, and they have all these crawlers
going around the internet.
And what you end up doing basically
is you start with a few seed web pages,
and then you follow all the links.
And you just keep following links,
and you keep indexing all the information,
and you end up with a ton of data of the internet over time.
So this is usually the starting point for a lot of these efforts.
Now this common crawl data is quite raw
and is filtered in many, many different ways.
So here they document, this is the same diagram.
They document a little bit the kind of processing
that happens in these stages.
So the first thing here is something called URL filter.
So what that is referring to is that there
is these block lists of basically URLs
that are or domains that you don't want
to be getting data from.
So usually this includes things like malware websites,
spam websites, marketing websites, racist websites,
adult sites, and things like that.
So there's some of the different types of websites
that are just eliminated at this stage
because we don't want them in our dataset.
The second part is text extraction.
You have to remember that all of these web pages,
this is the raw HTML of these web pages that are being saved
by these crawlers.
So when I go to inspect here,
This is what the raw HTML actually looks like.
You'll notice that it's got all this markup like lists
and stuff like that and their CSS and all this kind of stuff.
So this is computer code almost for these web pages.
But what we really want is we just want this text, right?
We just want the text of this web page
and we don't want the navigation and things like that.
So there's a lot of filtering and processing
and heuristics that go into adequately filtering
for just the good content of these web pages.
The next stage here is language filtering.
So for example, a fine web filters using a language classifier.
They try to guess what language every single web page is in.
And then they only keep web pages that
have more than 65% of English as an example.
And so you can get a sense that this is
like a design decision that different companies can take
for themselves.
What fraction of all different types of languages
are we going to include in our data set?
Because for example, if we filter out
all of the Spanish as an example, then
You might imagine that our model later will not be very good at Spanish because it's just
never seen that much data of that language.
And so different companies can focus on multi-langual performance to a different degree
as an example.
So fine web is quite focused on English, and so their language model, if they end up
training one later, will be very good at English, but not maybe very good at other languages.
After language filtering, there's a few other filtering steps and deduplication and things
like that, finishing with, for example, the PII removal.
This is personally identifiable information.
So as an example, addresses, social security numbers,
and things like that, you would try to detect them
and you would try to filter out those kinds of web pages
from the data set as well.
So there's a lot of stages here
and I won't go into full detail,
but it is a fairly extensive part of the pre-processing
and you end up with, for example, the fine web data set.
So when you click in on it, you can see some examples here
of what this actually ends up looking like,
and anyone can download this on the Hanging Face webpage.
And so here's some examples of the final text
that ends up in the training set.
So this is some article about tornadoes in 2012.
So there's some tornadoes in 2020 and 2012
and what happened.
This next one is something about,
did you know you have two little yellow nine volt battery sized
adrenal glands in your body?
Okay, so this is kind of an odd medical article.
So just think of these as basically
web pages on the internet filtered just for the text
in various ways.
And now we have a ton of text, 40 terabytes of it.
And that now is the starting point
for the next step of this stage.
Now I wanted to give you an intuitive sense
of where we are right now.
So I took the first 200 web pages here
and remember we have tons of them.
And I just take all that text
and I just put it all together, concatenated.
And so this is what we end up with.
We just get this just raw text, raw internet text.
And there's a ton of it, even in these 200 web pages.
So I can continue zooming out here.
And we just have this massive tapestry of text data.
And this text data has all these patterns.
And what we want to do now is we want
to start training neural networks on this data.
So the neural hours can internalize and model
how this text flows, right?
So we just have this giant texture of text
and now we want to get neural lots that mimic it.
Okay, now before we plug text into neural networks,
we have to decide how we're going to represent this text
and how we're gonna feed it in.
Now, the way our technology works for these neural lots
is that they expect a one-dimensional sequence of symbols
and they want a finite set of symbols that are possible.
And so we have to decide what are the symbols
and then we have to represent our data
as one dimensional sequence of those symbols.
So right now what we have is a one dimensional sequence
of text.
It starts here and it goes here and then it comes here, etc.
So this is one dimensional sequence
even though on my monitor, of course,
it's laid out in a two dimensional way
but it goes from left to right and top to bottom, right?
So it's a one dimensional sequence of text.
Now this being computers, of course,
there's an underlying representation here.
So if I do what's called UTF-8 encode this text,
then I can get the raw bits that correspond
to this text in the computer.
And that looks like this.
So it turns out that, for example,
this very first bar here is the first eight bits
as an example.
So what is this thing, right?
This is a representation that we are looking for
in the circumstance.
We have exactly two possible symbols,
zero and one, and we have a very long sequence of it, right?
Now, as it turns out, this sequence length is actually going to be very finite and
precious resource in our neural network, and we actually don't want extremely long sequences
of just two symbols. Instead, what we want is we want to trade off this symbol size
of this vocabulary, as we call it, and the resulting sequence length. So, we don't want
just two symbols and extremely long sequences, we're going to want more symbols and shorter sequences.
Okay, so one naive way of compressing or decreasing the length of our sequence here is to basically
consider some group of consecutive bits, for example, eight bits and group them into a single
what's called byte. So because these bits are either on or off, if we take a group of eight of them,
there turns out to be only 256 possible combinations of how these bits could be honor off.
And so therefore we can re-represent this sequence into a sequence of bytes instead.
So this sequence of bytes will be 8 times shorter, but now we have 256 possible symbols.
So every number here goes from 0 to 255.
Now I really encourage you to think of these not as numbers, but as unique IDs or like unique symbols.
So, maybe it's a bit more, maybe it's better to actually think of these, to replace every one of these with a unique emoji.
You'd get something like this.
So, we basically have a sequence of emojis and there's 256 possible emojis. You can think of it that way.
Now, it turns out that in production for state-of-the-art language models, you actually want to go even beyond this.
He wants to continue to shrink the length of the sequence because again it is a precious resource in return for more symbols in your vocabulary.
And the way this is done is done by running what's called the byte pair encoding algorithm.
And the way this works is we're basically looking for consecutive bytes or symbols that are very common.
So for example, it turns out that the sequence 116 followed by 32 is quite common and occurs
very frequently.
So what we're going to do is we're going to group this pair into a new symbol.
So we're going to mint a symbol with an ID256 and we're going to rewrite every single
pair 116 and 32 with this new symbol.
And then we can iterate this algorithm as many times as we wish.
And each time when we mint a new symbol, we're decreasing the length and we're increasing
the symbol size. And in practice it turns out that a pretty good setting of the basically
the vocabulary size turns out to be about 100,000 possible symbols. So in particular GPT-4
uses 100,000 and 277 symbols. And this process of converting from raw text into these symbols
or as we call them tokens, is the process called tokenization.
So let's now take a look at how GPT-4 performs tokenization,
converting from text to tokens and from tokens back to text,
and what this actually looks like.
So one website I like to use to explore
these token representations is called tick tokenizer.
And so come here to the dropdown and select CL100K base,
which is the GPT-4 base model tokenizer.
And here on the left, you can put in text,
And it shows you the tokenization of that text.
So for example, have low space world.
So hello world turns out to be exactly two tokens.
The token hello, which is the token with ID 15339
and the token space world, that is the token 1917.
So hello space world.
Now if I was to join these two for example,
I'm gonna get again two tokens
it's the token h, followed by the token yellow world without the h. If I put in two spaces here
between hello and world, it's again a different tokenization. There's a new token to 20 here.
Okay, so you can play with this and see what happens here. Also keep in mind this is not,
this is case sensitive. So if this is a capital h, it is something else. Or if it's hello world,
then actually this ends up being three tokens instead of just two tokens.
Yeah, so you can play with this and get in sort of like an intuitive sense of what these tokens work like.
We're actually going to loop around to colonization a bit later in the video. For now, I just wanted to show you the website.
And I wanted to show you that this text, basically, at the end of the day, so for example, if I take one line here,
this is what GPT-4 will see it as. So this text will be a sequence of length 62.
This is the sequence here. And this is how the chunks of text correspond to
these symbols. And again, there's 100,277 possible symbols. And we now have one
dimensional sequences of those symbols. So yeah, we're going to come back to
tokenization, but that's from now where we are. Okay, so what I've done now is I've
taken this sequence of text that we have here in the data set and I have
represented it using our tokenizer into a sequence of tokens. And this is
what that looks like now. So for example, when we go back to define what data set, they
mentioned that not only is this 44 terabytes of disk space, but this is about a 15 trillion
token sequence in this data set. And so here, these are just some of the first one or two
or three or a few thousand here, I think tokens of this data set, but there's 15 trillion
here to keep in mind. And again, keep in mind one more time that all of these represent
little text chunks, they're all disliked atoms of these sequences, and the numbers here
don't make any sense. They're just unique IDs.
So now we get to the fun part, which is the neural network training. And this is where a
lot of the heavy lifting happens computationally when you're training these neural networks.
So what we do here in this step is we want to model the statistical relationships of how
these tokens follow each other in the sequence.
So what we do is we come into the data and we take windows of tokens.
So we take a window of tokens from this data fairly randomly.
And the window's length can range anywhere between zero tokens, actually, all the way
up to some maximum size that we decide on.
So for example, in practice, you could see a token windows of, say, 8,000 tokens.
Now, in principle, we can use arbitrary window lengths of tokens, but processing very
long, basically window sequences would just be very computationally expensive.
So we just kind of decide that say 8,000 is a good number or 4,000 or 16,000, and we
crop it there.
Now in this example, I'm going to be taking the first four tokens just so everything
fits nicely.
So these tokens, we're going to take a window of 4 tokens, this bar view, hing, and space
single, which are these token IDs.
And now what we're trying to do here is we're trying to basically predict the token that comes
next in a sequence.
So 3962 comes next, right?
So what we do now here is that we call this the context.
These 4 tokens are context, and they feed into a neural network.
And this is the input to the neural work.
Now I'm going to go into the detail of what's inside this neural network in a little bit.
For now, it's important to understand is the input and the output of the neural net.
So the input are sequences of tokens of variable length, anywhere between zero and some maximum
size, like 8000.
The output now is a prediction for what comes next.
So because our vocabulary has 100,277 possible tokens, the neural network is going to output
exactly that many numbers and all of those numbers correspond to the probability of that
token as coming next in the sequence. So it's making guesses about what comes next.
In the beginning, this neural network is randomly initialized. So we're going to see in a
little bit of what that means. But it's a random transformation. So these probabilities
in the very beginning of the training are also going to be kind of random. So here I have
three examples, but keep in mind that there's 100,000 numbers here.
So the probability of this token, space direction,
neural network is saying that this is 4% luckily right now.
11,799 is 2%.
And then here, the probability of 3962, which is post, is 30%.
Now, of course, we've sampled this window from our data set.
So we know what comes next. We know, and that's the label.
We know that the correct answer is this 3962 actually comes next in the sequence.
So now what we have is this mathematical process for doing an update to the neural network.
We have a way of tuning it and we're going to go into a little bit of detail in a bit.
But basically we know that this probability here of 3%, we want this probability to be higher
and we want the probabilities of all the other tokens to be lower.
And so we have a way of mathematically calculating how to adjust and update the neural network so
So that the correct answer has a slightly higher probability.
So if I do an update to the neural network now, the next time I feed this particular sequence
of 4 tokens into the neural network, the neural network will be slightly adjusted now and
it will say, okay, post this maybe 4% and case now maybe is 1% and direction could become
2% or something like that.
And so we have a way of nudging of slightly updating the neural net to basically give
the higher probability to the correct token that comes next in the sequence.
And I would just have to remember that this process happens not just for this token here
where these four fed in and predicted this one.
This process happens at the same time for all of these tokens in the entire dataset.
And so in practice, we sample little windows, little batches of windows, and then at every
single one of these tokens, we want to adjust our neural networks so that the probability
of that token becomes slightly higher.
And this all happens in parallel in large batches of these tokens.
And this is the process of training the neural network.
It's a sequence of updating it so that its predictions match up the statistics of what actually
happens in your training set.
And its probabilities become consistent with the statistical patterns of how these tokens
follow each other in the data.
So let's not briefly get into the internals of these neural networks just to give you a
sense of what's inside.
neural network internals. So as I mentioned, we have these inputs that are sequences of tokens.
In this case, this is four input tokens, but this can be anywhere between zero up to,
let's say, a thousand tokens. In principle, this can be an infinite number of tokens.
It would just be too computational expensive to process an infinite number of tokens.
So we just crop at a certain length, and that becomes the maximum context length of that model.
Now, these inputs x are mixed up in a giant mathematical expression together with the parameters
or the weights of these neural networks.
So here I'm showing six example parameters and they're setting.
But in practice, these modern neural networks will have billions of these parameters.
And in the beginning, these parameters are completely randomly set.
Now, with a random setting of parameters,
you might expect that this neural network
would make random predictions, and it does.
In the beginning, it's totally random predictions.
But it's through this process of iteratively updating
the network, and we call that process training a neural
work, so that the setting of these parameters
gets adjusted, such that the outputs of our neural work
becomes consistent with the patterns
seen in our training set.
So think of these parameters as kind of like knobs on a DJ set.
And as you're twiddling these knobs,
you're getting different predictions
for every possible token sequence input.
And training neural network just means discovering
a setting of parameters that seems to be consistent
with the statistics of the training set.
Now, let me just give you an example
of what this giant mathematical expression looks like
just to give you a sense.
And modern networks are massive expressions
with trillions of terms probably.
But let me just show you a simple example here.
It would look something like this.
I mean, these are the kinds of expressions,
just to show you that it's not very scary.
We have inputs x, like x1, x2, in this case,
two example inputs, and they get mixed up
with the weights of the network, w0, w1, 2, 3, et cetera.
And this mixing is simple things
like multiplication, addition,
exponentiation, division, et cetera.
And it is the subject of neural network architecture research
to design effective mathematical expressions
that have a lot of kind of convenient characteristics
that are expressive, they're optimizable,
they're a parallelizable, et cetera.
And so, but at the end of the day,
these are not complex expressions,
and basically they mix up the inputs with the parameters
to make predictions,
and we're optimizing the parameters of this neural network
so that the predictions come out consistent
with the training set.
Now, I would like to show you
an actual production grade example
of what these neural networks look like.
So for that, I encourage you to go to this website
that has a very nice visualization
of one of these networks.
So this is what you will find on this website.
And this neural network here
that is used in production settings
has this special kind of structure.
This network is called the transformer.
And this particular one as an example
has 85,000 roughly parameters.
Now here on the top, we take the inputs
which are the token sequences.
And then information flows through the neural network
until the output, which here are the legit softmax,
but these are the predictions for what comes next,
what token comes next.
And then here, there's a sequence of transformations
and all these intermediate values
that get produced inside this mathematical expression
as it is sort of predicting what comes next.
So as an example, these tokens are embedded
into kind of like this distributed representation as it's called.
So every possible token has kind of like a vector
that represents it inside the neural network.
So first we embed the tokens
and then those values kind of like flow through this diagram.
And these are all very simple mathematical expressions
individually.
So we have layer norms and matrix multiplications
and softmaxes and so on.
So here's kind of like the attention block
of this transformer.
And then information kind of flows through
into the multilayer perception block and so on.
And all these numbers here,
these are the intermediate values of their expression.
And you can almost think of these as kind of like
the firing rates of these synthetic neurons.
But I would caution you to not kind of think of it
too much like neurons because these are extremely simple
neurons compared to the neurons you would find in your brain.
Your biological neurons are very complex dynamical
processes that have memory and so on.
There's no memory in this expression.
It's a fixed mathematical expression
from input to output with no memory.
It's just a stateless.
So these are very simple neurons
in comparison to biological neurons,
but you can still kind of loosely think of this
as like a synthetic piece of brain tissue
if you like to think about it that way.
So information flows through all these neurons
fire until we get to the predictions.
Now, I'm not actually going to dwell too much
on the precise kind of like mathematical details
of all these transformations.
Honestly, I don't think it's that important to get into.
What's really important to understand
is that this is a mathematical function.
It is parametrized by some fixed set of parameters,
like say, 85,000 of them.
And it is a way of transforming inputs into outputs.
And as we're twiddling the parameters,
we are getting different kinds of predictions.
And then we need to find a good setting of these parameters
so that the predictions sort of match up
with the patterns seen in training set.
So that's the transformer.
Okay, so I've shown you the internals of the neural network
and we talked a bit about the process of training it.
I want to cover one more major stage
of working with these networks
and that is the stage called inference.
So an inference what we're doing
is we're generating new data from the model.
And so we want to basically see
what kind of patterns it has internalized
in the parameters of its network.
So to generate from the model is relatively straightforward.
We start with some tokens that are basically your prefix,
like what you want to start with.
So same we want to start with the token 91.
Well, we feed it into the network,
and remember that the network gives us probabilities, right?
It gives us this probability vector here.
So what we can do now is we can basically flip a biased coin.
So we can sample basically a token based
on this probability distribution.
So the tokens that are given high probability
by the model are more likely to be sampled
when you flip this biased coin.
You can think of it that way.
So we sample from the distribution
to get a single unique token.
So for example, token 860 comes next.
So 860 in this case, when we're generating
from model could come next.
Now, 860 is a relatively likely token.
It might not be the only possible token in this case.
There could be many other tokens
that could have been sampled.
But we could see that 860 is a relatively likely token
as an example, and indeed in our training example here,
860 does follow 91.
So let's not say that we continue the process.
So after 91, there's a 60, we append it,
and we again ask, what is the third token?
Let's sample, and let's just say that it's 287.
Exactly as here.
Let's do that again.
We come back in.
Now we have a sequence of three, and we ask,
what is the likely fourth token?
And we sample from that and get this one.
And now let's see we do it one more time.
We take those four, we sample, and we get this one.
And this 13659, this is not actually 3962
as we had before.
So this token is the token article, instead.
So viewing a single article.
And so in this case, we didn't exactly reproduce
the sequence that we saw here in the training data.
So keep in mind that these systems are stochastic.
They have, we're sampling, and we're flipping
coins and sometimes we lock out and we reproduce some like small chunk of the text and
training set, but sometimes we're getting a token that was not verbatim part of any
of the documents in the training data. So we're going to get sort of like remixes of the data
that we saw in the training because at every step of the way, we can flip and get a slightly
different token and then once that token makes it in, if you sample the next one and so on,
You very quickly start to generate token streams that are very different from the token streams that occur in the training documents.
So statistically, they will have similar properties, but they are not identical to training data.
They're kind of like inspired by the training data.
And so in this case, we got a slightly different sequence.
And why would we get article?
You might imagine that article is a relatively likely token in the context of bar viewing, single, etc.
and you could imagine that the word article
followed this context window,
somewhere in the training documents to some extent
and we just happened to sample it here at that stage.
So basically inference is just predicting
from these distributions one at a time,
we continue feeding back tokens and getting the next one.
And we're always flipping these coins
and depending on how lucky or unlucky we get,
we might get very different kinds of patterns
depending on how we sample
from these probability distributions.
So that's inference.
So in most common scenarios,
basically downloading the internet
and tokenizing it as a pre-processing step,
you do that a single time.
And then once you have your token sequence,
we can start training networks.
And in practical cases,
you would try to train many different networks
of different kinds of settings
and different kinds of arrangements
and different kinds of sizes.
And so you'd be doing a lot of neural network training
And then once you have a neural network and you train it,
and you have some specific set of parameters
that you're happy with, then you can take the model
and you can do inference.
And you can actually generate data from the model.
And when you're on charge GPT and you're talking
with the model, that model is trained
and has been trained by OpenAI many months ago, probably.
And they have a specific set of weights that work well.
And when you're talking to the model,
all of that is just inference.
There's no more training.
those parameters are held fixed,
and you're just talking to the model sort of.
You're giving it some of the tokens,
and it's kind of completing token sequences.
And that's what you're seeing generated
when you actually use the model on chat GPT.
So that model then just does inference alone.
So let's now look at an example of training an inference
that is kind of concrete,
and gives you a sense of what this actually looks like
when these models are trained.
Now the example that I would like to work with
and that I'm particularly fond of
is that of OpenAI's GPT-2.
So GPT stands for generically pre-trained transformer,
and this is the second iteration
of the GPT series by OpenAI.
When you are talking to chat GPT today,
the model that is underlying all of the magic
of that interaction is GPT-4.
So the fourth iteration of that series.
Now GPT-2 was published in 2019 by OpenAI
in this paper that I have right here.
And the reason I like GPT-2 is that it is the first time
that a recognizably modern stack came together.
So all of the pieces of GPT2 are recognizable today
by modern standards, it's just everything has gotten bigger.
Now I'm not gonna be able to go into the full details
of this paper, of course,
because it is a technical publication,
but some of the details that I would like
to highlight are as follows.
GPT2 was a transformer neural network,
just like the neural networks you would work with today.
It was, it had 1.6 billion parameters, right?
So these are the parameters that we looked at here.
It would have 1.6 billion of them.
Today, modern transformers would have a lot closer
to a trillion or several hundred billion probably.
The maximum context length here was 1,024 tokens.
So it is when we are sampling chunks of windows
of tokens from the data set.
We're never taking more than 1,024 tokens.
And so when you are trying to predict the next token
in a sequence, you will never have more than 1,024 tokens
kind of in your context in order to make that prediction.
Now, this is also tiny by modern standards.
Today, the context lengths would be a lot closer
to a couple hundred thousand,
or maybe even a million.
And so you have a lot more context,
a lot more tokens in history.
And you can make a lot better prediction
about the next token in a sequence in that way.
And finally, GP2 was trained on approximately
100 billion tokens.
And this is also fairly small by modern standards.
As I mentioned, the fine web data set that we looked at here,
The final database that has 15 trillion tokens,
so 100 billion is quite small.
Now, I actually tried to reproduce GPD2 for fun
as part of this project called lm.c.
So you can see my write up of doing that
in this post on GitHub under the lm.c repository.
So in particular, the cost of training GPD2 in 2019
was estimated to be approximately $40,000.
But today you can do significantly better than that.
In particular, here I took about one day and about $600.
But this wasn't even trying too hard.
I think you could really bring this down
to about $100 today.
Now, why is it that the costs have come down so much?
Well, number one, these datasets have gotten a lot better.
And the way we filter them, extract them,
and prepare them has gotten a lot more refined.
And so the dataset is of just a lot higher quality,
so that's one thing.
But really the biggest difference
is that our computers have gotten much faster
in terms of the hardware,
and we're gonna look at that in a second.
And also the software for running these models
and really squeezing out all the speed from the hardware
as it is possible,
that software has also gotten much better
as everyone has focused on these models
and trying to run them very, very quickly.
Now, I'm not gonna be able to go into the full detail
of this GPT-2 reproduction,
and this is a long technical post,
but I would like to still give you an intuitive sense
for what it looks like to actually train one of these models
as a researcher, like what are you looking at
and what does it look like?
What does it feel like?
So let me give you a sense of that a little bit.
Okay, so this is what it looks like.
Let me slide this over.
So what I'm doing here is I am training a GPT-2 model
right now.
And what's happening here is that every single line here
like this one is one update to the model.
So remember how here we are basically making
the prediction better for every one of these tokens and we are updating these weights or
parameters of the neural net.
So here every single line is one update to the neural network where we change its parameters
by a little bit so that it is better at predicting the next token in the sequence.
In particular, every single line here is improving the prediction on one million tokens in the
training set.
So we've basically taken one million tokens out of this data set and we've tried to improve
the prediction of that token as coming next in a sequence on all one million of them simultaneously.
And at every single one of these steps, we are making an update to the network for that.
Now the number to watch closely is this number called loss. And the loss is a single number
that is telling you how well your neural network is performing right now. And it is created so that
low loss is good. So you'll see that the loss is decreasing as we make more updates to the neural
not, which corresponds to making better predictions on a next token in a sequence.
And so the loss is the number that you are watching as a neural network researcher.
And you are kind of waiting, you're twiddling your thumbs, you're drinking coffee, and
you're making sure that this looks good so that with every update your loss is improving
and the network is getting better at prediction.
Now here, you see that we are processing one million tokens per update.
Each update takes about seven seconds roughly.
And here we are going to process a total of 32,000 steps of optimization.
So 32,000 steps with 1 million tokens each is about 33 billion tokens that we are going
to process.
And we're currently only about 420, step 420 out of 32,000.
So we are still only a bit more than 1% done because I've only been running this for
10 or 15 minutes or something like that.
Now every 20 steps, I have configured this optimization to do inference.
So what you're seeing here is the model is predicting the next token in a sequence.
And so you sort of started randomly and then you continue plugging in the tokens.
So we're running this inference step.
And this is the model sort of predicting the next token in a sequence and every time
you see something appear, that's a new token.
So let's just look at this and you can see that this is not yet very coherent and keep
in mind that this is only 1% of the way through training.
And so the model is not yet very good at predicting the next token in a sequence.
So what comes out is actually kind of a little bit of gibberish, right?
But it still has a little bit of like local coherence.
So since she is mine, it's a part of the information should discuss my father, great companions,
Gordon showed me sitting over it and etc.
So I know it doesn't look very good, but let's actually scroll up and see what it looked
like when I started the optimization.
So all the way here at step one.
So after 20 steps of optimization, you see that what we're getting here is looks completely
random.
And of course, that's because the model has only had 20 updates to its parameters.
And so it's given you a random text because it's a random network.
And so you can see that at least in comparison to this, the model is starting to do much better.
And indeed, if we waited the entire 32,000 steps, the model will have improved the point
that it's actually generating fairly coherent English.
the tokens stream correctly, and they kind of make up English a lot better.
So this has to run for about a day or two more now, and so at this stage, we just make
sure that the loss is decreasing, everything is looking good, and we just have to wait.
And now, let me turn now to the story of the computation that's required, because of
course, I'm not running this optimization on my laptop.
That would be way too expensive because we have
to run this neural network and we have to improve it
and we need all this data and so on.
So you can't run this too well on your computer
because the network is just too large.
So all of this is running on a computer
that is out there in the cloud.
And I want to basically address the compute side of the story
of training these models and what that looks like.
So let's take a look.
Okay, so the computer that I'm running this optimization on
is this 8xH100 node.
So there are eight H100s in a single node
or a single computer.
Now, I am renting this computer
and it is somewhere in the cloud.
I'm not sure where it is physically actually.
The place I like to rent from is called Lambda
but there are many other companies who provide this service.
So when you scroll down,
you can see that they have some on-demand pricing
for sort of computers that have these H100s,
which are GPUs.
and I'm going to show you what they look like in a second.
But on demand eight times a video, H100 GPU,
this machine comes for $3 per GPU per hour, for example.
So you can rent these and then you get a machine
in a cloud and you can go in and you can train these models.
And these GPUs, they look like this.
So this is one H100 GPU, this is kind of what it looks like
and you slot this into your computer.
And GPUs are this perfect fit
for training neural networks, because they are very
computationally expensive, but they
display a lot of parallelism in the computation.
So you can have many independent workers working
all at the same time in solving the matrix multiplication
that's under the hood of training these neural networks.
So this is just one of these H100s,
but actually you would put multiple of them together.
So you could stack eight of them into a single node,
and then you can stack multiple nodes
into an entire data center, or an entire system.
So when we look at a data center,
when we look at a data center,
we start to see things that look like this.
So we have one GPU, goes to AGPUs,
goes to a single system, goes to many systems.
And so these are the bigger data centers
and there, of course, would be much, much more expensive.
And what's happening is that all the big tech companies
really desire these GPUs so they can train
all these language models
because they are so powerful.
And that is fundamentally what has driven the stock price
of NVIDIA to be $3.4 trillion today as an example.
And why NVIDIA has kind of exploded.
So this is the gold rush.
The gold rush is getting the GPUs, getting enough of them
so they can all collaborate to perform this optimization.
And they're, what are they all doing?
They're all collaborating to predict the next token
on a data set like the find what data set.
This is the computational overflow
that basically is extremely expensive.
The more GPUs you have, the more tokens
you can try to predict and improve on.
And you're gonna process this data set faster,
and you can iterate faster and get a bigger network,
and train a bigger network, and so on.
So this is all those machines that are doing,
and this is why all of this is such a big deal.
And for example, this is a article
from like about a month ago or so.
This is why it's a big deal.
For example, Elon Musk is getting 100,000 GPUs
in a single data center.
And all of these GPUs are extremely expensive,
are going to take a ton of power,
and all of them are just trying to predict the next token
in the sequence and improve the network by doing so.
And get probably a lot more coherent text
than what we're seeing here, a lot faster.
Okay, so unfortunately, I do not have a couple of 10
or a hundred million of dollars
to spend on training a really big model like this,
but luckily we can turn to some big tech companies
who train these models routinely
and release some of them once they are done training.
So they've spent a huge amount of compute
to train this network and they release the network
at the end of the optimization.
So it's very useful because it's done a lot of compute for that.
So there are many companies who train these models routinely,
but actually not many of them release
these what's called base models.
So the model that comes out at the end here
is what's called a base model.
What is a base model?
It's a token simulator, right?
It's an internet text token simulator.
And so that is not by itself useful yet,
because what we want is what's called an assistant.
We want to ask questions and have it respond to answers.
These models won't do that.
They just create sort of remixes of the internet.
They dream internet pages.
So the base models are not very often released
because they're kind of just only a step one
of a few other steps that we still need to take
to get an assistant.
However, a few releases have been made.
So as an example, the GPT2 model released the 1.6 billion,
sorry, 1.5 billion model back in 2019.
And this GPT2 model is a base model.
Now what is a model release?
What does it look like to release these models?
So this is the GPT2 repository on GitHub.
Well, you need two things basically to release model.
Number one, we need the Python code usually
that describes the sequence of operations in detail that they make in their model.
So, if you remember back this transformer, the sequence of steps that are taken here
in this neural network is what is being described by this code.
So, this code is sort of implementing what's called forward pass of this neural network.
So, we need the specific details of exactly how they wired up that neural network.
So this is just computer code and it's usually just a couple hundred lines of code.
It's not that crazy and this is all fairly understandable and usually fairly standard.
What's not standard are the parameters.
That's where the actual value is.
Where are the parameters of this neural network?
Because there's 1.6 billion of them and we need the correct setting or a really good setting.
And so that's why in addition to this source code, they release the parameters,
which in this case is roughly 1.5 billion parameters.
And these are just numbers.
So it's one single list of 1.5 billion numbers.
The precise and good setting of all the knobs such that the tokens come out well.
So you need those two things to get a base model release.
Now GPT-2 was released, but that's actually a fairly old model, as I mentioned.
So actually the model we're going to turn to is called Lama 3.
And that's the one that I would like to show you next.
So Lama 3, so GPT2L again, was 1.6 billion parameters trained on 100 billion tokens.
Lama 3 is a much bigger model and much more modern model.
It is released and trained by Meta, and it is a 405 billion parameter model trained on 15
trillion tokens, in very much the same way just much, much bigger.
And Meta has also made a release of Lama 3, and that was part of this paper.
So with this paper that goes into a lot of detail,
the biggest base model that they released
is the Atlanta 3.1 4.5,
405 billion parameter model.
So this is the base model.
And then in addition to the base model,
if you see here, foreshadowing,
four later sections of the video,
they also released the instruct model.
And the instruct means that this is an assistant.
You can ask it questions and it will give you answers.
We still have yet to cover that part later.
For now, let's just look at this base model,
this token simulator, and let's play with it
and try to think about, you know, what is this thing
and how does it work and what do we get
at the end of this optimization
if you let this run until the end
for a very big neural network on a lot of data.
So my favorite place to interact with the base models
is this company called HypeBalloc
which is basically serving the base model
of the 405D Lama 3.1.
So when you go to the website
and I think you may have to register and so on,
make sure that in the models,
make sure that you are using Lama 3.1
for a five billion base, it must be the base model.
And then here, let's say the max tokens
is how many tokens we're going to be generating.
So let's just decrease this to be a bit less
just so we don't waste compute.
We just want the next 128 tokens
and leave the other stuff alone.
I'm not going to go into the full detail here.
Now, fundamentally, what's going to happen here
is identical to what happens here during inference for us.
So this is just going to continue the token sequence
of whatever prefix you're going to give it.
So I want to first show you that this model here
is not yet an assistant.
So you can't, for example, ask it, what is 2 plus 2?
It's not going to tell you, oh, it's 4.
What else can I help you with?
It's not going to do that.
Because what is 2 plus 2 is going to be tokenized.
And then those tokens just access a prefix.
And then what the model is going to do now
is just going to get the probability for the next token.
And it's just a glorified autocomplete.
It's a very, very expensive autocomplete
of what comes next.
Depending on the statistics of what it's all,
and its training documents, which are basically web pages.
So let's just hit enter to see what tokens
it comes up with as a continuation.
Okay, so here it kind of actually answered the question
and it started to go off into some philosophical territory.
Let's try it again.
So let me copy and paste and let's try again from scratch.
What does 2 plus 2?
So okay, so it just goes off again.
So notice one more thing that I want to stress
is that the system, I think every time you put it in,
it just kind of starts from scratch.
So the system here is stochastic.
So for the same prefix of tokens,
we're always getting a different answer.
And the reason for that is that we get this problem
to distribution and we sample from it,
and we always get different samples,
and we sort of always go into a different territory afterwards.
So here in this case, I don't know what this is.
Let's try one more time.
So just continues on.
So it's just doing the stuff that it's on the internet, right?
And it's just kind of like regurgitating
those statistical patterns.
So first things, it's not an assistant yet.
It's a token autocomplete.
And second, it is a stochastic system.
Now, the crucial thing is that even though this model
is not yet by itself very useful for a lot of applications
just yet, it is still very useful because in the task
of predicting the next token in the sequence,
the model has learned a lot about the world.
And it has stored all that knowledge
in the parameters of the network.
So remember that our text looked like this,
internet web pages.
And now all of this is sort of compressed
in the weights of the network.
So you can think of these 405 billion parameters
as a kind of compression of the internet.
You can think of the 405 billion parameters
as kind of like a zip file,
but it's not a lossless compression,
it's a lossy compression.
We're kind of like left with kind of a gestalt of the internet
and we can generate from it, right?
Now, we can elicit some of this knowledge
by prompting the base model accordingly.
So for example, here's a prompt that might work
to elicit some of that knowledge that's hiding in the parameters.
Here's my top 10 list of the top 10 marks to see in pairs.
And I'm doing it this way because I'm trying to prime the model
to now continue this list.
So let's see if that works when I press enter.
Okay?
So you see that it started the list
and it's now kind of giving me some of those landmarks.
And I notice that it's trying to give a lot of information
here now, you might not be able to actually fully trust
some of the information here.
Remember that this is all just a recollection
of some of the internet documents.
And so the things that occur very frequently
in the internet data are probably more likely
to be remembered correctly compared to things
that have happened very infrequently.
So you can't fully trust some of the things
that is some of the information that is here
because it's all just a vague recollection
of internet documents.
Because the information is not stored explicitly
in any of the parameters.
It's all just the recollection.
That's that we did get something
that is probably approximately correct.
And I don't actually have the expertise to verify
that this is roughly correct.
But you see that we've elicited
a lot of the knowledge of the model.
And this knowledge is not precise and exact.
This knowledge is vague and probabilistic and statistical.
And the kinds of things that occur often
are the kinds of things that are more likely
to be remembered in the model.
Now, I want to show you a few more examples
of this model's behavior.
The first thing I want to show you
is this example.
I went to the Wikipedia page for Zebra,
and let me just copy paste the first even one sentence here.
And let me put it here.
Now, when I click Enter, what kind of completion
are we going to get?
So let me just hit Enter.
There are three living species, et cetera, et cetera.
What the model is producing here is an exact regurgitation
of this Wikipedia entry.
It is reciting this Wikipedia entry purely from memory
and this memory is stored in its parameters.
And so it is possible that at some point
in these 512 tokens, the model will stray away
from the Wikipedia entry.
But you can see that it has huge chunks of it memorized here.
Let me see, for example, if this sentence occurs by now.
OK, so we're still on track.
Let me check here.
OK, we're still on track.
it will eventually stray away.
Okay, so this thing is just to recite it
to a very large extent.
It will eventually deviate
because it won't be able to remember exactly.
Now, the reason that this happens
is because these models can be extremely good at memorization.
And usually this is not what you want in the final model,
and this is something called recursion,
and it's usually undesirable to cite things
directly that you have trained on.
Now, the reason that this happens actually
is because for a lot of documents,
Like, for example, Wikipedia, when these documents are deemed to be of very high quality as a source,
like, for example, Wikipedia, it is very often the case that when you train the model,
you will preferentially sample from those sources.
So basically, the model has probably done a few epochs on this data,
meaning that it has seen this web page, like maybe probably 10 times or so.
And it's a bit like you, like when you read some kind of a text many, many times,
say you read something a hundred times, then you will be able to recite it.
And it's very similar for this model.
If it sees something way too often,
it's going to be able to recite it later from memory.
Except these models can be a lot more efficient
at like per presentation than a human.
So probably it's only seen this Wikipedia entry 10 times,
but basically it has remembered this article
exactly in its parameters.
OK, the next thing I'm going to show you
is something that the model has definitely not seen
during its training.
So for example, if we go to the paper
and then we navigate to the pre-training data,
We'll see here that the dataset has a knowledge cutoff
until the end of 2023.
So it will not have seen documents after this point.
And certainly it has not seen anything
about the 2024 election and how it turned out.
Now, if we prime the model with the tokens from the future,
it will continue the token sequence
and it will just take its best guess,
according to the knowledge that it has in its own parameters.
So let's take a look at what that could look like.
So the Republican Party could Trump,
okay, President of the United States from 2017,
and let's see what it says after this point.
So for example, the model will have to guess
at the running mate and who it's against, et cetera.
So let's hit enter.
So here are things that Mike Pence was the running mate
instead of JD Ves.
And the ticket was against Hillary Clinton and Tim Cain.
So this is kind of an interesting parallel universe
potentially of what could have happened
according to the alarm.
Let's get a different sample.
So the identical prompt and let's re-sample.
So here the running mate was Ron DeSantis
and they ran against Joe Biden and Kamala Harris.
So this is again a different parallel universe.
So the model will take educated guesses
and it will continue the token sequence
based on this knowledge.
And it will just kind of like all we're seeing here
is what's called hallucination.
The model is just taking its best guess
in a probabilistic manner.
The next thing I would like to show you
is that even though this is a base model
and not yet an assistant model,
it can still be utilized in particle applications.
If you are clever with your prompt design.
So here's something that we would call a few shot prompt.
So what it is here is that I have 10 words or 10 pairs.
And each pair is a word of English, colon,
and then the translation in Korean.
And we have 10 of them.
And what the model does here is at the end,
we have teacher, colon,
And then here's where we're gonna do a completion
of say just fact tokens.
And these models have what we call
in-context learning abilities.
And what that's referring to is that
as it is reading this context,
it is learning sort of in place
that there's some kind of an algorithmic pattern
going on in my data.
And it knows to continue that pattern.
And this is called kind of like in-context learning.
So it takes on the role of a translator
and when we hit completion,
we see that the teacher translation is
Sonsanim, which is correct.
And so this is how you can build apps
by being clever with your prompting,
even though we still just have a base model for now.
And it relies on what we call this
in context learning ability
and it is done by constructing what's called
a few shot prompt.
Okay, and finally,
I want to show you that there is a clever way
to actually instantiate a whole language model
assistant just by prompting.
And the trick to it is that we're gonna structure a prompt
to look like a web page that is a conversation
between a helpful AI assistant and a human.
And then the model will continue that conversation.
So actually, to write the prompt,
I turned to chat GPT itself, which is kind of meta.
But I told it, I want to create an all in assistant,
but all I have is the base model.
So can you please write my prompt?
And this is what it came up with,
which is actually quite good.
So here's a conversation between an AI assistant and a human.
The AI assistant is knowledgeable, helpful,
capable of answering wider IT questions, et cetera.
And then here, it's not enough to just give it a sort of description.
It works much better if you create this few shot prompt.
So here's a few terms of human assistant, human assistant.
And we have a few terms of conversation.
And then here at the end is we're going to be putting the actual query that we like.
So let me copy paste this into the base model prompt.
And now, let me do a human column.
And this is where we put our actual prompt.
Why is this sky blue?
And let's run assistant.
The sky appears blue due to the phenomenon
called Raylite scattering, et cetera, et cetera.
So you see that the base model is just
continuing the sequence.
But because the sequence looks like this conversation,
it takes on that role.
But it is a little subtle because here it just, you know,
it ends the assistant and then just, you know,
hallucinates the next question by the human, et cetera.
So we'll just continue going on and on.
But you can see that we have a sort of accomplished a task.
And if you just took this, why is this kind of blue?
And if we just refresh this and put it here,
then of course, we don't expect this to work
with a base model, right?
We're just going to, who knows what we're going to get?
Okay, we're just going to get more questions.
Okay, so this is one way to create an assistant,
even though you may only have a base model.
Okay, so this is the kind of brief summary
of the things we talked about over the last few minutes.
Now, let me zoom out here,
and this is kind of like what we've talked about so far.
We wish to train alarm assistants like ChachyBT.
We've discussed the first stage of that,
which is the pre-training stage,
and we saw that really what it comes down to
is we take internet documents,
we break them up into these tokens,
these atoms of little text chunks,
and then we predict token sequences using neural networks.
The output of this entire stage is this base model.
It is the setting of the parameters of this network.
And this base model is basically
an internet document simulator on the token level.
So it can just, it can generate token sequences
that have the same kind of like statistics
as internet documents.
And we saw that we can use it in some applications,
but we actually need to do better.
We want an assistant.
We want to be able to ask questions
and we want the model to give us answers.
And so we need to now go into the second stage,
which is called the post training stage.
So we take our base model, our internal document simulator,
and hand it off to post-training.
So we're now going to discuss a few ways
to do what's called post-training of these models.
These stages in post-training are
going to be computationally much less expensive,
most of the computational work, all of the massive data
centers, and all of the heavy compute and millions of dollars
are the pre-training stage.
But now we're going to the slightly cheaper,
but still extremely important stage called post-training,
where we turn this LLM model into an assistant.
So let's take a look at how we can get our model
to not sample internet documents,
but to give answers to questions.
So in other words, what we want to do
is we want to start thinking about conversations.
And these are conversations that can be multi-turned,
so that we multiple turns.
And they are, in the simplest case,
a conversation between a human and an assistant.
And so for example, we can imagine
that the conversation could look something like this.
When a human says what is 2 plus 2,
the assistant should respond with something like 2 plus 2 is 4.
When a human follows up and says, what if it was star instead of a plus?
Assistant could respond with something like this.
And similar here, this is another example showing that the assistant could also have
some kind of a personality here that it's kind of like nice.
And then here on the third example, I'm showing that when a human is asking for something
that we don't wish to help with, we can produce what's called a refusal.
We can say that we cannot help with that.
So in other words, what we want to do now is we want to think through
how an assistant should interact with the human.
And we want to program the assistant
and its behavior in these conversations.
Now, because this is neural networks,
we're not going to be programming these explicitly in code.
We're not going to be able to program the assistant
in that way.
Because this is neural networks,
everything is done through neural network training
on data sets.
And so because of that,
we are going to be implicitly programming the assistant
by creating data sets of conversations.
So these are three independent examples of conversations
in a data set.
An actual data set, and I'm going to show you examples,
will be much larger.
It could have hundreds of thousands of conversations
that are multi-turned, very long, et cetera,
and would cover a diverse breadth of topics.
But here I'm only showing three examples.
By the way, this works basically is assistant
is being programmed by example.
And where is this data coming from,
like two times two equals four, same as two plus two, et cetera?
Where does that come from?
This comes from human laborers.
So we will basically give human laborers
some conversational context.
And we will ask them to basically give
the ideal assistant response in this situation.
And a human will write out the ideal response
for an assistant in any situation.
And then we're gonna get the model
to basically train on this
and to imitate those kinds of responses.
So the way this works then
is we are going to take our base model
which we produced in the pre-training stage.
And this base model was trained on internet documents.
We're now going to take that data set of internet documents
and we're going to throw it out.
And we're going to substitute a new data set.
And that's going to be a data set of conversations.
And we're going to continue training
the model on these conversations,
on this new data set of conversations.
And what happens is that the model will very rapidly adjust
and will sort of like learn the statistics
of how this assistant responds to human queries.
And then later during inference,
we'll be able to basically prime the assistant
and get the response,
and it will be imitating what the human lablers would do
in that situation, if that makes sense.
So we're gonna see examples of that,
and this is gonna become a bit more concrete.
I also wanted to mention that this post training stage
we're gonna basically just continue training the model,
but the pre training stage can in practice
take roughly three months of training
on many thousands of computers.
The post training stage will typically be much shorter
like three hours, for example.
And that's because the data set of conversations
that we're going to create here manually
is much more smaller than the data set of text on the internet.
And so this training will be very short,
but fundamentally, we're just going to take our base model,
we're going to continue training using the exact same algorithm,
the exact same everything, except we're
swapping out the data set for conversations.
So the questions now are, where are these conversations?
How do we represent them?
How do we get the model to see conversations
instead of just raw text?
And then what are the outcomes of this kind of training?
And what do you get in a certain psychological sense
when we talk about the model?
So let's turn to those questions now.
So let's start by talking about the tokenization
of conversations.
Everything in these models has to be turned into tokens.
Because everything is just about token sequences.
So how do we turn conversations into token sequences
is the question.
And so for that, we need to design some kind of end encoding.
And this is kind of similar to maybe if you're familiar,
you don't have to be with, for example, the TCP IP packet
on the internet.
There are precise rules and protocols
for how you represent information,
how everything is structured together,
so that you have all this kind of data laid out
in a way that is written out on a paper
and that everyone can agree on.
And so it's the same thing now happening in all elements.
We need some kind of data structures,
and we need to have some rules around how these data structures,
like conversations, get encoded and decoded to and from tokens.
And so I want to show you now how I would recreate
this conversation in the token space.
So if you go to TickTokenizer, I can take that conversation,
and this is how it is represented
in for the language model.
So here we have, we are iterating a user
and an assistant in this two-turned conversation.
And what you're seeing here is it looks ugly,
but it's actually relatively simple.
The way it gets turned into a token sequence here at the end
is a little bit complicated, but at the end,
this conversation between a user and assistant
ends up being 49 tokens.
It is a one-dimensional sequence of 49 tokens,
and these are the tokens, okay?
And all the different LLMs
will have a slightly different format or protocols,
and it's a little bit of a Wild West right now,
but, for example, GPT-4O does it in the following way.
You have this special token called IM underscore start,
And this is short for imaginary monologue of the start.
Then you have to specify, I don't actually
know why it's called that, to be honest.
Then you have to specify who's turn it is.
So for example, user, which is a token 1, 4, 2, 8.
Then you have internal monologue separator.
And then it's the exact question.
So the tokens of the question.
And then you have to close it.
So I am end, the end of the imaginary monologue.
So basically, the question from a user
of what is 2 plus 2 ends up being
the token sequence of these tokens.
And the important thing to mention here is that I am start.
This is not text, right?
I am start is a special token that gets added.
It's a new token.
And this token has never been trained on so far.
It is a new token that we create
in a post-training stage, and we introduce.
And so these special tokens like I am set, I am start, et cetera,
are introduced and interspersed with text
so that they sort of get the model to learn
that hey, this is the start of a turn for,
who is it the start of the turn for,
the start of the turn is for the user.
And then this is what the user says,
and then the user ends.
And then it's a new start of a turn
and it is by the assistant.
And then what does the assistant say?
Well, these are the tokens of what the assistant says, et cetera.
And so this conversation has not turned into
this sequence of tokens.
The specific details here are not actually that important.
All I'm trying to show you in concrete terms
is that our conversations, which we think of as kind of
like a structured object, end up being turned via some encoding
into one-dimensional sequences at tokens.
And so because this is one-dimensional sequence of tokens,
we can apply all this stuff that we applied before.
Now it's just a sequence of tokens,
and now we can train a language model on it.
And so we're just predicting the next token in a sequence,
just like before and we can represent
and train on conversations.
And then what does it look like at test time during inference?
So say we've trained a model and we've trained a model
on these kinds of data sets of conversations.
And now we want to inference.
So during inference, what does this look like
when you're on chassis PT?
Well, you come to chassis PT and you have say
like a dialogue with it.
And the way this works is basically say
that this was already filled in.
So like, what is 2 plus 2, 2 plus 2 is 4?
And now you issue what, if it was times, I am end.
And what basically ends up happening
on the servers of open AI or something like that,
is they put an I am start assistant, I am set,
and this is where they end it right here.
So they construct this context,
and now they start sampling from the model.
So it's at this stage that they will go to the model
and say, okay, what is a good first sequence?
What is a good first token?
What is a good second token?
what is a good third token.
And this is where the LM takes over
and creates a response.
Like for example, response that looks something like this
but it doesn't have to be identical to this
but it will have the flavor of this
if this kind of a conversation was in the dataset.
So that's roughly how the protocol works
although the details of this protocol are not important.
So again, my goal is that just to show you
that everything ends up being
just a one-dimensional token sequence
so we can apply everything we've already seen
but we're not training on conversations
and we're now basically generating conversations as well.
Okay, so now I would like to turn to
what these data sets look like in practice.
The first paper that I would like to show you
and the first effort in this direction
is this paper from OpenAI in 2022.
And this paper was called Instruct GPT
or the technique that they developed.
And this was the first time that OpenAI has kind of talked
about how you can take language models
and fine tune them on conversations.
And so this paper has a number of details
I would like to take you through.
So the first stop I would like to make
is in section 3.4, where they talk about the human contractors
that they hired, in this case,
from Upwork or through SKLI,
to construct these conversations.
And so there are human laborers involved
whose job it is professionally to create these conversations.
And these laborers are asked to come up with prompts
and then they are asked to also complete
the ideal assistant responses.
And so these are the kinds of problems
that people came up with.
So these are human laborers.
So list five ideas for how to regain enthusiasm for my career.
What are the top 10 science fiction books I should read next?
And there's many different types of kind of prompts here.
So translate this sentence to Spanish, et cetera.
And so there's many things here that people came up with.
They first come up with the prompt,
and then they also answer that prompt,
and they give the ideal assistant response.
Now, how do they know what is the ideal assistant response
that they should write for these prompts?
So when we scroll down a little bit further,
we see that here we have this excerpt
of labeling instructions that are given to the human
labelers.
So the company that is developing the language model,
like for example, OpenAI, writes up labeling instructions
for how the humans should create ideal responses.
And so here, for example, is an excerpt
of these kinds of labeling instructions.
On a high level, you're asking people to be helpful,
truthful, and harmless.
And you can pause the video if you'd like to see more here.
But on a high level, basically just answer,
try to be helpful, try to be truthful,
and don't answer questions that we don't want
kind of the system to handle later in chat GPT.
And so roughly speaking,
the company comes up with the labeling instructions.
Usually they are not this short.
Usually they are hundreds of pages,
and people have to study them professionally.
And then they write out the ideal assistant responses
following those labeling instructions.
So this is a very human-heavy process
as it was described in this paper.
Now, the data set for InstructGPT
was never actually released by OpenAI,
but we do have some open source reproductions
that were trying to follow this kind of a setup
and collect their own data.
So one that I'm familiar with, for example,
is the effort of Open Assistant from a while back.
And this is just one of, I think, many examples,
but I just wanna show you an example.
So here's, so these are people on the internet
that were asked to basically create these conversations
similar to what opening I did with human laborers.
And so here's an entry of a person
who came up with this prompt.
Can you write a short introduction
to their relevance of the term monopsony in economics,
please use examples, et cetera?
And then the same person, or potentially a different person,
will write up the response.
So here's the assistant response to this.
And so then the same person or different person
will actually write out this ideal response.
And then this is an example of maybe
how the conversation could continue.
Now explain it to a dog,
and then you can try to come up with
a slightly simpler explanation or something like that.
Now, this then becomes the label
and we end up training on this.
So what happens during training is that,
of course we're not gonna have a full coverage
of all the possible questions
that the model will encounter at test time during inference.
We can't possibly cover all the possible prompts
that people are gonna be asking
the future. But if we have like a data set of a few of these examples, then the model during
training will start to take on this persona of this helpful, truthful, harmless assistant.
And it's all programmed by example. And so these are all examples of behavior. And if you have
conversations of these example behaviors and you have enough of them like 100,000 and you train
on it, the model sort of starts to understand the statistical pattern and it kind of takes on this
personality of this assistant. Now, it's possible that when you get the exact same question
like this at test time, it's possible that the answer will be recited as exactly what
was in the training set, but more likely than that is that the model will kind of like do
something of a similar vibe. And we will understand that this is the kind of answer that you want.
So that's what we're doing. We're programming the system by example in the system adopts
statistically, this persona of this helpful,
truthful, harmless assistant,
which is kind of like reflected
in the labeling instructions that the company creates.
Now I want to show you that the state of the artist
has kind of advanced in the last two or three years
since the Instructivity paper.
So in particular, it's not very common for humans
to be doing all the heavy lifting
just by themselves anymore.
And that's because we now have language models
and these language models are helping us
create these data sets and conversations.
So it is very rare that the people will
will literally just write out the response from scratch.
It is a lot more likely that they will use an existing LLM
to basically come up with an answer
and then they will edit it or things like that.
So there's many different ways in which now LLM
started to kind of permeate this post-training stack.
And LLMs are basically used
or basically to help create these massive
data sets of conversations.
So I don't want to show like UltraChat
is one such example of like a more modern data set
of conversations, it is to a very large extent synthetic,
but I believe there's some human involvement.
I could be wrong with that.
Usually there will be a little bit of human,
but there will be a huge amount of synthetic help.
And this is all kind of like constructing in different ways.
And ultra-shadows is just one example
of many SFT data sets that currently exist.
And the only thing I wanna show you is that
these data sets have now millions of conversations.
These conversations are mostly synthetic,
but they're probably edited to some extent by humans.
and they span a huge diversity of areas and so on.
So these are fairly extensive artifacts by now
and there are all these like SFT mixtures as they're called.
So you have a mixture of like lots of different types
and sources and it's partially synthetic, partially human.
And it's kind of like gone in that direction since.
But roughly speaking, we still have SFT data sets.
They're made up of conversations.
We're training on them, just like we did before.
And I guess like the last thing to note is that I want to dispel a little bit of the
magic of talking to an AI.
Like when you go to Chatchee PT and you give it a question and then you hit enter, what
is coming back is kind of like statistically aligned with what's happening in the training
set.
And these training sets, I mean, they really just have a seed in humans following labeling
instructions.
So what are you actually talking to in ChashiPT or how should you think about it?
Well it's not coming from some magical AI, like roughly speaking.
It's coming from something that is statistically imitating human laborers, which comes
from labeling instructions written by these companies.
And so you're kind of imitating this, you're kind of getting, it's almost as if you're
asking human laborer.
And imagine that the answer that is given to you from ChashiPT is some kind of a simulation
of a human labeler and it's kind of like asking what would a human labeler say in this
kind of a conversation and it's not just like the human labeler is not just like a random
person from the internet because these companies actually hire experts.
So for example, when you are asking questions about code and so on, the human labeler that
would be involved in creation of these conversation data sets, they would usually be educated
expert people. And you're kind of like asking a question of like a simulation of those people,
if that makes sense. So you're not talking to a magical AI, you're talking to an average
labular, this average labular is probably fairly highly skilled, but you're talking to kind of
like an instantaneous simulation of that kind of a person that would be hired in the construction
of these data sets. So let me give you one more specific example before we move on. For example,
when I go to Chatchy PT and I say, recommend the top five landmarks you've seen pairs. And then I
hit enter. Oh, okay, here we go. Okay, when I hit enter, what's coming out here, how do
I think about it? Well, it's not some kind of a magical AI that has gone out and researched
all the landmarks and then ranked them using its infinite intelligence, et cetera. What
I'm getting is a statistical simulation of a labeler that was hired by OpenAI. You can
think about it roughly in that way. And so if this specific question is in the post-training
dataset somewhere at OpenAI. Then I'm very likely to see an answer that is probably very
very similar to what that human labeler would have put down for those five landmarks.
How does the human labeler come up with this? Well, they go off and they go on the internet
and they kind of do their own little research for 20 minutes and they just come up with a list,
right? Now, so if they come up with this list and this is in the dataset, I'm probably very likely
to see what they submitted as the correct answer from the assistant. Now, if this specific query
is not part of the post-training data set,
then what I'm getting here is a little bit more emergent.
Because the model kind of understands this statistically,
the kinds of landmarks that are in a string set
are usually the prominent landmarks.
They're landmarks that people usually want to see.
The kinds of landmarks that are usually
very often talked about on the internet.
And remember that the model already has a ton of knowledge
from its pre-training on the internet.
So it's probably seen a ton of conversations about pairs
about landmarks, about the kinds of things
that people like to see.
And so it's the pre-trained knowledge that is then combined
with the post-trained data set that results
in this kind of an imitation.
So that's roughly how you can kind of think about
what's happening behind the scenes here
in the statistical sense.
Okay, now I want to turn to the topic of LLM psychology
as I like to call it,
which is where sort of the emergent cognitive effects
of the training pipeline that we have for these models.
So in particular, the first one I want to talk to
is of course hallucinations.
So you might be familiar with model hallucinations.
It's when LLMS makes stuff up.
They just totally fabricate information, et cetera.
And it's a big problem with LLMS systems.
It is a problem that existed to a large extent
with early models for many years ago.
And I think the problem has gotten a bit better
because there are some mitigations
that I'm going to go into in a second.
For now, let's just try to understand
where these hallucinations come from.
So here's a specific example of a few of three conversations
that you might think you have in your training set.
And these are pretty reasonable conversations
that you could imagine being in the training set.
So like, for example, who is Tom Cruise?
Well, Tom Cruise is in a famous actor,
American actor and producer, et cetera.
Who is John Barrasso?
This turns out to be a US Senator, for example.
Who is Genghis Khan?
Well, Genghis Khan was blah, blah, blah.
And so this is what your conversations
could look like at training time.
Now, the problem with this is that
When the human is writing the correct answer
for the assistant, in each one of these cases,
the human either like knows who this person is
or they research them on the internet
and they come in and they write this response
that kind of has this like confident tone of an answer.
And what happens basically is that at test time,
when you ask for someone who is,
this is a totally random name that I totally came up with
and I don't think this person exists, as far as I know,
I just try to generate it randomly.
The problem is when we ask who is Orson Kovats,
The problem is that the assistant will not just tell you,
oh, I don't know.
Even if the assistant and the language model itself
might know inside its features, inside its activations,
inside of its brain sort of,
it might know that this person is like not someone
that it's familiar with,
even if some part of the network kind of knows that
in some sense.
The saying that, oh, I don't know who this is,
is not going to happen because the model
Statistically imitates is training set.
In the training set, the questions of the form
who is blah are confidently answered
with the correct answer.
And so it's going to take on the style of the answer
and it's going to do its best.
It's going to give you statistically
the most likely guess.
And it's just going to basically make stuff up.
Because these models, again, we just talked about it
is they don't have access to the internet.
They're not doing research.
These are statistical token tumblers, as I call them,
as just trying to sample the next token in the sequence.
And it's going to basically make stuff up.
So let's take a look at what this looks like.
I have here what's called an inference playground
from Hugging Face.
And I am on purpose picking on a model called Falcon 7B,
which is an old model.
This is a few years ago now.
So it's an older model.
So it suffers from hallucinations.
And as I mentioned, this has improved over time recently.
But let's say who is Orson Kobat's
let's ask Falcon 7B and start.
Run?
Oh yeah, Orson Kobat's is an American author
science fiction writer, okay. This is totally false. It's Hallucination. Let's try again. These are
statistical systems, right, so we can resample. This time, Orson Kobat is a fictional character
from this 1950s TV show. This is total BS, right? Let's try again. He's a former minor league
baseball player. Okay, so basically the model doesn't know. And it's given us lots of different
answers because it doesn't know. It's just kind of like sampling from these probabilities.
the model starts with the tokens who is Orson Kobat's assistant and then it comes in here
and it's good it's getting these probabilities and it's just sampling from the probabilities
and it just like comes up with stuff and the stuff is actually statistically consistent
with the style of the answer in its training set and it's just doing that but you and I
experienced it as a made up factual knowledge but keep in mind that the model basically doesn't know
and it's just imitating the format of the answer and it's not going to go off and look it up
because it's just imitating again the answer. So how can we mitigate this? Because for example,
when we go to chat GPT and I say who is Orson Kovats and I'm now asking the state-of-the-art model
for you to play I, this model will tell you. So this model is actually even smarter because you
saw very briefly it said searching the web. We're going to cover this later. It's actually trying to
to do tool use and kind of just like came up with some kind of a story.
But I want to just do not use any tools.
I don't want it to do web search.
There's a well known historical public failure named or or some covots.
So this model is not going to make up stuff.
This model knows that it doesn't know and it tells you that it doesn't appear
to be a person that this model knows.
So somehow we sort of improved host nations,
even though they clearly are an issue in older models.
And it makes totally sense why you would be getting
these kinds of answers if this is what your training set looks like.
So how do we fix this?
Well, clearly, we need some examples in our data set
that where the correct answer for the assistant
is that the model doesn't know about some particular fact.
But we only need to have those answers be produced
in the cases where the model actually doesn't know.
And so the question is how do we know what the model knows or doesn't know
Well, we can empirically probe the model to figure that out.
So let's take a look at, for example, how meta dealt with hallucinations
for the Lama 3e series of models as an example.
So in this paper that they published from meta,
we can go into hallucinations, which they call here factuality,
and they describe the procedure by which they basically interrogate the model
to figure out what it knows and doesn't know,
to figure out sort of like the boundary of its knowledge.
And then they add examples to the training set, where for the things where the model doesn't
know them, the correct answer is that the model doesn't know them, which sounds like a very easy
thing to do in principle. But this roughly fixes the issue. And the reason it fixes the issue is
because remember that the model might actually have a pretty good model of its self-knowledge
inside the network. So remember we looked at the network and all these neurons inside the network.
You might imagine that there's a neuron somewhere in the network that sort of lights up
for when the model is uncertain. But the problem is that the activation of that neuron is not
currently wired up to the model actually saying in words that it doesn't know. So even though the
internals of the neural network know because there's some neurons that represent that,
But the model will not surface that, it will instead take its best guess so that it sounds
confident just like it sees in the training set.
So we need to basically interrogate the model and allow it to say, I don't know, in the
cases that it doesn't know.
So let me take you through what Meta roughly does.
So basically what they do is here I have an example, Dominic Kashek is the featured article
today, so I just went there randomly, and what they do is basically they take a random
document in a training set, and they take a paragraph, and then they use an LLM to construct
questions about that paragraph.
So for example, I did that with chat GPT here.
So I said, here's a paragraph from this document, generate three specific factual questions
based on this paragraph, and give me the questions and the answers.
And so the LLMs are already good enough to create and reframe this information.
So if the information is in the context window of this all-em, this actually works pretty
well.
It doesn't have to rely on its memory.
It's right there in the context window.
And so it can basically reframe that information with fairly high accuracy.
So for example, can generate questions for us like, for which team that he play, here's
the answer, how many cups of D1, etc.
And now what we have to do is we have some question and answers.
And now we want to interrogate the model.
So roughly speaking, what we'll do is we'll take our questions and we'll go to our model,
which would be a salama in meta.
But let's just interrogate Mistral7b here as an example, that's another model.
So does this model know about this answer?
Let's take a look.
So he played for Buffalo Sabers, right?
So the model knows.
And the way that you can programmatically decide is basically we're going to take this
answer from the model, and we're going to compare it to the correct answer.
And again, the models are good enough to do this automatically.
So there's no humans involved here.
We can take basically the answer from the model, and we can use another LLM judge to check
if that is correct according to this answer.
And if it is correct, that means that the model probably knows.
So what we're going to do is we're going to do this maybe a few times.
So okay, it knows it's Buffalo Sabers.
Let's try it in.
Buffalo Sabers.
one more time, Buffalo Sabers. So we asked three times about this factual question and the model
seems to know so everything is great. Now let's try the second question. How many Stanley Cup did
he win? And again, let's interrogate the model about that and the correct answer is two. So
here the model claims that he won four times, which is not correct, right? It doesn't match two.
So the model doesn't know it's making stuff up.
Let's try again.
So here the model, again, is kind of like making stuff up, right?
Here it says it didn't, he did not even, did not win during his career.
So obviously the model doesn't know.
And the way we can programmatically tell again,
is we interrogate the model three times
and we compare its answers, maybe three times, five times,
whatever it is, to the correct answer.
And if the model doesn't know, then we know that the model doesn't know this question.
question. And then what we do is we take this question, we create a new
conversation in the training set. So we're going to add a new conversation
training set. And when the question is, how many standing cups did he win?
The answer is, I'm sorry, I don't know, or I don't remember. And that's the
correct answer for this question. Because we interrogated the model and we saw
that that's the case. If you do this for many different types of questions,
for many different types of documents, you are given the model an
opportunity to in its training set refuse to say based on its knowledge, and if you just
have a few examples of that in your training set, the model will know and has the opportunity
to learn the association of this knowledge-based refusal to this internal neuron similar
in its network that we presume exists, and empirically this turns out to be probably the case.
And it can learn that association that, hey, when this neuron of uncertainty is high,
then I actually don't know.
And I'm allowed to say that I'm sorry,
but I don't think I remember this, et cetera.
And if you have these examples in your training set,
then this is a large mitigation for hallucination.
And that's roughly speaking why tragedy
is able to do stuff like this as well.
So these are the kinds of mitigations
that people have implemented
and that have improved the factuality issue over time.
Okay, so I've described mitigation number one
for basically mitigating the hallucinations issue.
Now, we can actually do much better than that.
It's instead of just saying that we don't know,
we can introduce an additional mitigation number two
to give the LLM an opportunity
to be factual and actually answer the question.
Now, what do you and I do if I was to ask you
a factual question and you don't know,
what would you do in order to answer the question?
Well, you could go off and do some search
and use the internet and you could figure out the answer
and then tell me what that answer is.
And we can do the exact same thing with these models.
So think of the knowledge inside the neural network
inside its billions of parameters.
Think of that as kind of a vague recollection
of the things that the model has seen
during its training during the pre-training stage
a long time ago.
So think of that knowledge in the parameters
as something you read a month ago.
And if you keep reading something,
then you will remember it and the model remembers that.
But if it's something rare,
then you probably don't have a relative recollection
of that information.
But what you and I do is we just go and look it up.
Now, when you go and look it up,
what you're doing basically is like
you're refreshing your working memory with information
and then you're able to sort of like retrieve it,
talk about it, or et cetera.
So we need some equivalent of allowing the model
to refresh its memory or its recollection.
And we can do that by introducing tools for the models.
So the way we are going to approach this is that
Instead of just saying, hey, I'm sorry, I don't know,
we can attempt to use tools.
So we can create a mechanism by which the language model
can emit special tokens.
And these are tokens that we're going to introduce
new tokens.
So for example, here I've introduced two tokens
and I've introduced a format or protocol
for how the model is allowed to use these tokens.
So for example, instead of answering the question,
when the model does not, instead of just saying,
I don't know, sorry,
The model has the option now to emitting the special token search start.
And this is the query that will go to like Bing.com in a case of OpenAI or say Google search
or something like that.
So it will emit the query and then it will emit search end.
And then here what will happen is that the program that is sampling from the model that
is running the inference, when it sees the special token search end, instead of sampling
the next token in the sequence, it will actually pause generating from the
model. It will go off. It will open a session with Bing.com and it will paste
the search query into Bing and it will then get all the text that is
retrieved and it will basically take that text. It will maybe represent it
again with some other special tokens or something like that and it will take
that text and it will copy-paste it here into what I tried to like show
the brackets. So all that text kind of comes here. And when the text comes here, it enters the
context window. So the model, so that text from the web search is now inside the context window
that will feed into the neural network. And you should think of the context window as kind of
like the working memory of the model. That data that is in the context window is directly accessible
by the model. It directly feeds into the neural network. So it's not anymore a vague recollection.
It's data that it has in the context window and is directly available to that model.
So now when it's sampling the new tokens here afterwards,
it can reference very easily the data that has been copy-pasted in there.
So that's roughly how these tools function.
And so web search is just one of the tools.
We're going to look at some of the other tools in a bit.
But basically, you introduce new tokens.
You introduce some schema by which the model can utilize these tokens
and can call these special functions,
like web search functions.
And how do you teach the model
how to correctly use these tools,
like, say, web search, search, search, and et cetera?
Well, again, you do that through training sets.
So we need now to have a bunch of data
and a bunch of conversations
that show the model by example how to use web search.
So what are the settings where you are using the search?
And what does that look like?
And here's by example how you start a search and a search, et cetera.
And if you have a few thousand maybe examples of that
in your training set, the model will actually
do a pretty good job of understanding
how this tool works.
And it will know how to sort of structure its queries.
And of course, because of the pre-training data set
and its understanding of the world,
it actually kind of understands what a web search is.
And so it actually kind of has a pretty good native understanding
of what kind of stuff is a good search query.
And so it all kind of just like works.
You just need a little bit of a few examples
to show it how to use this new tool
and then it can lean on it to retrieve information
and put it in the context window
and that's equivalent to you and I looking something up.
Because once it's in the context,
it's in the working memory
and it's very easy to manipulate and access.
So that's what we saw a few minutes ago
when I was searching on ChatGPT
for who is Orson Kovats,
the ChatGPT language model decided
that this is some kind of a rare individual or something like that
and instead of giving me an answer from its memory,
it decided that it will sample a special token
that is gonna do a web search.
And we saw briefly something flash
was like using the web tool or something like that.
So it briefly said that
and then we waited for like two seconds
and then it generated this.
And you see how it's creating references here.
And so it's citing sources.
So what happened here is it went off,
it did a web search,
it found these sources and these URLs
and the text of these web pages
was all stuffed in between here
and it's not shown here, but it's basically stuffed as text
in between here.
And now it sees that text, and now it kind of references it,
and says that, okay, it could be these people,
citation, it could be those people, citation, et cetera.
So that's what happened here, and that's what,
and that's why when I said who is awesome covots,
I could also say, don't use any tools,
and then that's enough to basically convince
that you should not use tools and just use
its memory and its recollection.
I also went off and I tried to ask this question
of chat GPT, so how many standing cups did Dominic
Hashek win?
And chat GPT actually decided that it knows the answer
and it has the confidence to say that he won't twice.
And so it kind of just relied on its memory
because presumably it has enough of a kind of confidence
in its weights, its parameters and activations
that this is retrievable just for memory.
But you can also, conversely, use web search to make sure.
And then, for the same query, it actually goes off and it searches.
And then it finds a bunch of sources.
It finds all this.
All of this stuff gets copy-pasted in there.
And then it tells us two, again, and sites.
And it actually says the Wikipedia article, which is the source of this information for us as well.
So that's tools, web search.
The model determines when to search.
And then that's kind of like how these tools work.
And this is an additional kind of mitigation for hallucinations and
factuality.
So I want to stress one more time this very important sort of psychology point.
Knowledge in the parameters of the neural network is a vague recollection.
The knowledge and the tokens that make up the context window is the working memory.
And in roughly speaking works kind of like it works for us in our brain.
The stuff we remember is our parameters
and the stuff that we just experienced
like a few seconds or minutes ago and so on.
You can imagine that being in our context window
and this context window is being built up
as you have conscious experience around you.
So this is a bunch of implications also
for your use of L alums in practice.
So for example, I can go to chat GPT
and I can do something like this.
I can say can you summarize chapter one
of Jane Austen's Pride and Prejudice, right?
And this is a perfectly fine prompt.
And Cheshirept actually does something relatively reasonable
here.
And the reason it does that is because Cheshirept has a pretty
good recollection of a famous work like Pride and Precious.
It's probably seen a ton of stuff about it.
There's probably forums about this book.
It's probably read versions of this book.
And it's kind of like remembers because even if you've read
this or articles about it, you'd kind of have a recollection
enough to actually say all this.
But usually, when I actually interact with all of them,
and I want them to recall specific things,
it always works better if you just give it to them.
So I think a much better prompt would be something like this.
Can you summarize for me,
chapter one of Jane Austen's spread and prejudice,
and then I am attaching it below for your reference.
And then I do something like the limiter here,
and I paste it in.
And I found it just copy-pacing it
from some website that I found here.
So copy-pacing the chapter one here,
and I do that because when it's in the context window,
the model has direct access to it
and can exactly, it doesn't have to recall it,
it just has direct access to it.
And so this summary can be expected
to be a significantly high quality or higher quality
than this summary, just because it's directly available
to the model.
And I think you and I would work in the same way.
If you would produce a much better summary,
if you had reread this chapter before you had to summarize it.
And that's basically what's happening here
or the equivalent of it.
The next sort of psychological quirk I'd like
to talk about briefly is that of the knowledge of self.
So what I see very often on the internet
is that people do something like this.
They ask LLMs something like,
what model are you and who build you?
And basically this question is a little bit nonsensical.
And the reason I say that is that
as I try to kind of explain
with some of the under-the-hood fundamentals,
this thing is not a person, right?
It doesn't have a persistent existence in any way.
It sort of boots up, processes tokens, and shuts off.
And it does that for every single person.
It just kind of builds up a context window of conversation
and then everything gets deleted.
And so this entity is kind of like restarted
from scratch every single conversation, if that makes sense.
It has no persistent self, it has no sense of self,
it's token tumblr, and it files the statistical
regularities of its training set.
So it doesn't really make sense to ask it,
who are you, what built you, et cetera.
And by default, if you do what I described,
and just by default, and from nowhere,
you're gonna get some pretty random answers.
So for example, let's pick on Falcon,
which is a fairly old model,
And let's see what it tells us.
So it's evading the question, talented engineers
and developers.
Here it says, I was built by OpenAI based on a GPT-3 model.
It's totally making stuff up.
Now, the fact that it's built by OpenAI here,
I think a lot of people would take this as evidence
that this model was somehow trained in OpenAI data
or something like that.
I don't actually think that that's necessarily true.
The reason for that is that if you don't explicitly
program the model to answer these kinds of questions,
and what you're gonna get is its statistical best guess
at the answer.
And this model had a SFT data mixture of conversations
and during the fine tuning,
the model sort of understands as it's training on this data
that it's taking on this personality
of this like helpful assistant.
And it doesn't know how to,
it doesn't actually,
it wasn't told exactly what label to apply to self.
It just kind of is taking on this persona
of a helpful assistant.
And remember that the pre-training stage took
the documents from the entire internet.
And ChatGPT and OpenAI are very prominent in these documents.
And so I think what's actually likely to be happening here
is that this is just its hallucinated label
for what it is.
This is itself identity, is that it's ChatGPT by OpenAI.
And it's only saying that because there's a ton of data
on the internet of answers like this
that are actually coming from OpenAI from ChatGPT.
And so that's its label for what it is.
Now, you can override this as a developer.
If you have an LLM model, you can actually override it.
And there are a few ways to do that.
So for example, let me show you there's
this all model from Alan AI.
And this is one LLM.
It's not a top-tier LLM or anything like that,
but I like it because it's this fully open source.
So the paper for all-mo and everything else
is completely fully open source, which is nice.
So here we are looking at its SFT mixture.
So this is the data mixture of the fine tuning.
So this is the conversations data set, right?
And so the way that they are solving it
for the Olmo model is we see that there's a bunch of stuff
in the mixture and there's a total of 1 million
conversations here, but here we have Olmo2 hard coded.
If we go there, we see that this is 240 conversations.
And look at these 240 conversations.
They're hard coded.
Tell me about yourself, says user.
And then the assistant says, I'm Olmo,
and open the language model developed by AI2,
Allen Institute of Artificial Intelligence, et cetera.
I'm here to help blah, blah, blah.
What is your name?
The Omo project.
So these are all kinds of like
cooked up hard-coded questions about Omo2
and the correct answers to give in these cases.
If you take 240 questions like this or conversations,
put them into your training set and fine tune with it,
then the model will actually be expected
to parrot this stuff later.
If you don't give it this,
then it's probably a chashivity by an AI.
And there's one more way to sometimes do this is that,
basically, in these conversations, and you have turns between human and
assistant, sometimes there's a special message called system message
at the very beginning of the conversation. So it's not just between human and
assistant, there's a system. And in the system message, you can actually hard code
and remind the model that, hey, you are a model developed by open AI.
and your name is ChashiPity40 and you are trained on the state and your knowledge cut off is this
and basically it kind of like documents the model a little bit and then this is inserted into your
conversations so when you go on ChashiPity you see a blank page but actually the system message is
kind of like hidden in there and those tokens are in the context window and so those are the two ways
to kind of program the models to talk about themselves either it's done through data like this
or is done through system message and things like that basically invisible tokens that are in
the context window and remind the model of its identity. But it's all just kind of like
a cooked up and bolted on in some in some way. It's not actually like really deeply there in any
real sense as it would before even. I want to now continue to the next section which deals with
the computational capabilities or like I should say the native computational capabilities of these
models in problem solving scenarios. And so in particular we have to be very careful with these
models when we construct our examples of conversations and there's a lot of sharp edges here that are
kind of like elucidative, is that a word? They're kind of like interesting to look at when we consider
how these models think. So consider the following prompt from a human and suppose that basically that
we are building out a conversation to enter into our training set of conversations. So we're going
to train the model on this. We're teaching it how to basically solve simple math problems. So the
So the prompt is Emily buys three apples and two oranges, each orange costs two dollars,
the total cost is 13.
What is the cost of apples?
Very simple math question.
Now there are two answers here on the left and on the right.
They are both correct answers.
They both say that the answer is three, which is correct.
But one of these two is a significantly better answer for the assistant than the other.
Like if I was daily blur and I was creating one of these, one of these would be a really
terrible answer for the assistant and the other would be okay.
And so I'd like you to potentially pause the video even and think through why one of
these two is significantly better answer than the other.
And if you use the wrong one, your model will actually be really bad at math potentially
and they would have bad outcomes.
And this is something that you would be careful with in your labeling documentations when
you are training people to create the ideal responses for the assistant.
Okay, so the key to this question is to realize and remember that when the models are training
and also inferencing, they are working in one dimensional sequence of tokens from left
to right.
And this is the picture that I often have in my mind.
I imagine basically the token sequence evolving from left to right.
And to always produce the next token in the sequence, we are feeding all these tokens
into the neural network.
And this neural network think it is the probabilities for the next token in sequence, right?
So this picture here is the exact same picture we saw before up here.
And this comes from the web demo that I showed you before, right?
So this is the calculation that basically takes the input tokens here on the top and performs
these operations of all these neurons and gives you the answer for the probabilities
of what comes next.
Now, the important thing to realize is that roughly speaking, there's basically a finite
number of layers of computation that happen here.
So for example, this model here has only one, two, three layers of what's called attention
and MLB here.
Maybe a typical modern state-of-the-art network would have more, like say, a hundred layers
or something like that.
But there's only hundred layers of computation or something like that to go from the previous
token sequence to the probabilities for the next token.
And so there's a finite amount of computation that happens here for every single token.
And you should think of this as a very small amount of computation.
And this amount of computation is almost roughly fixed for every single token in this sequence.
That's not actually fully true because the more tokens you feed in, the more expensive
this forward pass will be of this neural network, but not by much.
So you should think of this, and I think as a good model to have in mind, this is a fixed
amount of compute that's going to happen in this box for every single one of these tokens.
And this amount of compute cannot possibly be too big because there's not that many layers
that are sort of going from the top to bottom here.
There's not that much computationally that will happen here.
So you can't imagine the model just to basically
do arbitrary computation in a single forward pass
to get a single token.
And so what that means is that we actually
have to distribute our reasoning and our computation
across many tokens, because every single token
is only spending a finite amount of computation on it.
And so we kind of want to distribute the computation across
many tokens and we can't have too much computation
or expect too much computation out of the model
in any single individual token
because there's only so much computation
that happens or token, okay?
Roughly fixed amount of computation here.
So that's why this answer here is significantly worse.
And the reason for that is,
imagine going from left to right here
and I copy-pasted it right here,
the answer is three, et cetera.
Imagine the model having to go from left to right
emitting these tokens one at a time.
It has to say, or we're expecting to say
the answer is space dollar sign.
And then right here, we're expecting it to basically
cram all the computation of this problem
into this single token.
It has to emit the correct answer, free.
And then once we've emitted the answer, free,
we're expecting it to say all these tokens,
but at this point, we've already produced the answer.
And it's already in the context window
for all these tokens that follow.
So anything here is just kind of post hoc justification
of why this is the answer, because the answer is already
created, it's already in the token window.
So it's not actually being calculated here.
And so if you are answering the question directly
and immediately, you are training the model
to try to basically guess the answer in a single token.
And that is just not going to work
because of the finite amount of computation
that happens per token.
That's why this answer on the right
is significantly better because we are distributing
this computation across the answer.
We're actually getting the model to slowly come to the answer.
From the left to right, we're getting intermediate results.
We're saying, OK, the total cost of oranges is 4.
So 13 minus 4 is 9.
And so we're creating intermediate calculations.
And each one of these calculations
is by itself not that expensive.
And so we're actually basically kind of guessing
a little bit the difficulty that the model is capable of
in any single one of these individual tokens.
And there can never be too much work
in any one of these tokens computationally
because then the model won't be able to do that later
at test time.
And so we're teaching the model here
to spread out its reasoning
and to spread out its computation over the tokens.
And in this way, it only has very simple problems
in each token and they can add up.
And then by the time it's nearly end,
it has all the previous results in its working memory
And it's much easier for it to determine that the answer is,
and here it is, three.
So this is a significantly better label for our computation.
This would be really bad, and it is teaching the model
to try to do all the computation in a single token.
It's really bad.
So that's kind of like an interesting thing to keep in mind
is in your prompt.
Usually you don't have to think about it explicitly
because the people at OpenAI have labelers and so on
that actually worry about this.
and make sure that the answers are spread out.
And so actually opening I will kind of like do the right thing.
So when I ask this question for Chatchy PT,
it's actually kind of go very slowly.
It's going to be like, okay, let's define our variables,
set up the equation,
and it's kind of creating all these intermediate results.
These are not for you.
These are for the model.
If the model is not creating these intermediate results
for itself, it's not going to be able to reach three.
I also wanted to show you that it's possible
to be a bit mean to the model.
We can just ask for things.
So as an example, I gave it the exact same prompt,
and I said, answer the question in a single token,
just immediately give me the answer, nothing else.
And it turns out that for this simple prompt here,
it actually was able to do it in a single go.
So it just created a single,
I think this is two tokens, right?
Because the dollar sign is its own token.
So basically, this model didn't give me a single token
and it gave me two tokens,
but it still produced the correct answer.
And it did that in a single forward pass of the network.
Now that's because the numbers here I think are very simple and so I made it a bit more difficult
to be a bit mean to the model. So I set Emily by 23 apples and 177 oranges and then I just made
the numbers a bit bigger and I'm just making it harder for the model. I'm asking you to do more
computation in a single token and so I set the same thing and here it gave me five and five is
actually not correct. So the model failed to do all this calculation in a single forward pass
of the network. It failed to go from the input tokens and then in a single forward pass of
the network, single go through the network, it couldn't produce the result. And then I said,
okay, now don't worry about the token limit and just solve the problem as usual. And then it goes
all the intermediate results. It simplifies and every one of these intermediate results here
and intermediate calculations is much easier for the model. And it's sort of it's not too much work
per token, all of the tokens here are correct, and it arises by solution, which is seven.
And it just couldn't squeeze all of this work. It couldn't squeeze that into a single
for a person network. So I think that's kind of just a cute example. And something to kind
of think about, and I think it's kind of, again, just elucidative in terms of how these models work.
The last thing that I would see on this topic is that if I was in practice trying to actually
solve this in my day-to-day life, I might actually not trust that the model that all the
bit intermediate calculations correctly here. So actually probably what I do is
something like this. I would come here and I would say use code. And that's
because code is one of the possible tools that chassis PD can use. And instead
of it having to do mental arithmetic, like this mental arithmetic here, I
don't fully trust it. And especially the numbers get really big. There's no
guarantee that the model will do this correctly. Any one of these intermediate
steps might impressible fail. We're using neural networks to do mental
arithmetic, kind of like you doing mental arithmetic in your brain. It might just like screw
up some of the intermediate results. It's actually kind of amazing that it can even do this
kind of mental arithmetic. I don't think I could do this in my head, but basically the
model is kind of like doing it in its head. And I don't trust that. So I wanted to use
tools. So you can say stuff like use code. And I'm not sure what happened there. Use code.
And so like I mentioned, there's a special tool and the model can write code. And I can
inspect that this code is correct.
And then it's not relying on its mental arithmetic.
It is using the Python interpreter,
which is a very simple programming language,
to basically write out the code that calculates the result.
And I would personally trust this a lot more
because this came out of the Python program,
which I think has a lot more correctness guarantees
than the mental arithmetic of a language model.
So just another kind of potential hint
that if you have these kinds of problems,
you may want to basically just ask the model
to use the code interpreter.
And just like we saw with the web search,
the model has special kind of tokens for calling.
Like it will not actually generate these tokens
from the language model, it will write the program
and then it actually sends that program
to a different sort of part of the computer
that actually just runs that program
and brings back the result.
And then the model gets access to that result
and can tell you that, okay, the cost of each apple is seven.
So that's another kind of tool
and I will use this in practice for yourself.
And it's just less error prone, I would say.
So that's why I called this section,
models need tokens to think.
Distribute your competition across many tokens,
ask models to create intermediate results,
or whenever you can, lean on tools and tool use,
instead of allowing the models
to do all of this stuff in their memory.
So if they try to do it all in their memory,
I don't fully trust it,
and prefer to use tools whenever possible.
I want to show you one more example of where this actually comes up and that's in counting.
So models actually are not very good at counting for the exact same reason.
You're asking for way too much in a single individual token.
So let me show you a simple example of that.
How many dots are below and then I just put in a bunch of dots.
And Cheshirept says there are and then it just tries to solve the problem in a single token.
So in a single token, it has to count the number of dots in its context window.
And it has to do that in a single forward pass over network.
In a single forward pass over network, as we talked about, there's not that much computation
that can happen there.
Just think of that as being like very little computation that happens there.
So if I just look at what the model sees, let's go to the LLN, go to tokenizer.
It sees this, how many dots are below.
And then it turns out that these dots here, this group of, I think, 20 dots is a single
token.
And then this group of whatever it is is another token.
And then for some reason, they break up as this.
So I don't actually, this has to do with the details of the tokenizer, but it turns out
that these, the model basically sees the token ID, this, this, this, and so on.
And then from these token IDs, it's expected to count the number.
in spoiler alert, it's not 161, it's actually I believe 177.
So here's what we can do instead.
We can say use code.
And you might expect that, like, why should this work?
And it's actually kind of subtle and kind of interesting.
So when I say use code, I actually
expect this to work, let's see.
OK, 177 is correct.
So what happens here is I've actually,
it doesn't look like it, but I've broken down
the problem into problems that are easier for the model.
I know that the model can't count.
it can't do mental counting.
But I know that the model is actually pretty good
at doing copy pasting.
So what I'm doing here is when I say use code,
it creates a string in Python for this
and the task of basically copy pasting my input here
to here is very simple.
Because for the model, it sees this string
of, it sees it as just these four tokens or whatever it is.
So it's very simple for the model
to copy paste those token IDs and kind of unpack them
into dots here.
And so it creates the string
and then it calls PythonRoutine.count
and then it comes up with the correct answer.
So the Python interpreter is doing the counting.
It's not the model's mental arithmetic
doing the counting.
So it's again the simple example of models need tokens
to think don't rely on their mental arithmetic
and that's why also the models are not very good at counting.
if you need them to do counting tasks,
always ask them to lean on the tool.
Now, the models also have many other
little cognitive deficits here and there,
and these are kind of like sharp edges of the technology
to be kind of aware of over time.
So as an example, the models are not very good
with all kinds of spelling related tasks.
They're not very good at it.
And I told you that we would loop back around
to tokenization.
And the reason to do this is that the models,
they don't see the characters, they see tokens.
And their entire world is about tokens,
which are these little text chunks.
And so they don't see characters like our eyes do.
And so very simple character level tasks often fail.
So for example, I'm giving it a string ubiquitous
and I'm asking it to print only every third character
starting with the first one.
So we start with you and then we should go every third.
So every, so one, two, three, Q should be next
and then et cetera.
So this IC is not correct.
And again, my hypothesis is that this is again,
Demental arithmetic here is failing.
Number one, a little bit.
But number two, I think the more important issue here
is that if you go to TikTok and Azure
and you look at ubiquitous,
we see that it is three tokens, right?
So you and I see ubiquitous
and we can easily access the individual letters
because we kind of see them.
And when we have it in the working memory
of our visual sort of field,
we can really easily index into every third letter
and I can do that task.
But the models don't have access to the individual letters.
They see this as these three tokens.
And remember, these models are trained from scratch
on the internet.
And basically the model has to discover
how many of all these different letters are packed
into all these different tokens.
And the reason we even use tokens is mostly for efficiency.
But I think a lot of people are interested
to delete tokens entirely.
Like we should really have character level
or byte level models.
It's just that that would create very long sequences
and people don't know how to deal with that right now.
So while we have the token world,
Any kind of spelling tasks are not actually expected
to work super well.
So because I know that spelling is not a strong suit
because of tokenization, I can again ask it to lean on tools.
So I can just say use code.
And I would, again, expect this to work
because the task of copy-pasting ubiquitous
into the Python interpreter is much easier.
And then we're leaning on Python interpreter
to manipulate the characters of this string.
So when I say use code, ubiquitous indexes
to every third character, and the actual truth is uq2s, uqts, which looks correct to me.
So again, an example of spelling related tasks not working very well. A very famous example
of that recently is how many are there in strawberry, and this one in the viral many times.
And basically the models now get it correct. They say there are three hours in strawberry,
but for a very long time, all the state of the art models would insist that there are
only two ars in strawberry. And this caused a lot of, you know,
a ruckus because is that it word? I think so, because it's just kind of like
why are the models so brilliant? And they can solve math Olympiad
questions, but they can't like count ars in strawberry. And the answer for
that, again, is I can't build up to it kind of slowly. But number one,
the models don't see characters they see tokens. And number two, they are not
very good at counting. And so here we are combining the difficulty of
seen the characters with the difficulty of counting.
And that's why the models struggled with this,
even though I think by now, honestly,
I think opening I may have hard coded the answer here,
or I'm not sure what they did,
but this specific query now works.
So models are not very good at spelling,
and there's a bunch of other little sharp edges,
and I don't want to go into all of them.
I just want to show you a few examples
of things to be aware of
and when you're using these models in practice.
I don't actually want to have a comprehensive analysis here,
all the ways that the models are kind of like falling short.
I just want to make the point that there are some jagged edges
here and there, and we've discussed a few of them
and a few of them make sense, but some of them also will
just not make as much sense.
And they're kind of like you're scratching your head
even if you understand in depth how these models work.
And a good example of that recently is the following.
The models are not very good at very simple questions
like this.
And this is shocking to a lot of people
because these problems can solve complex math problems.
They can answer PHD grade physics, chemistry, biology,
questions much better than I can,
but sometimes they fall short
and look super simple prompts like this.
So here we go, 9.11 is bigger than 9.9,
and it justifies it in some way, but obviously,
and then at the end, okay,
it actually flips its decision later.
So I don't believe that this is very reproducible.
Sometimes it flips around its answer,
sometimes gets it rise, sometimes gets it wrong.
let's try again. Okay, even though it might look larger. Okay, so here doesn't even correct
itself in the end. If you ask many times, sometimes it gets it right too. But how is it
that the model can do so great at Olympiad grade problems, but then fail on very simple problems
like this? And I think this one, as I mentioned, a little bit of a head scratcher. It turns
out that a bunch of people studied this in depth, and I haven't actually read the paper,
But what I was told by this team was that when you scrutinize the activations inside the
neural network, when you look at some of the features and what features turn on or off
and what neurons turn on or off, a bunch of neurons inside the neural network light up that
are usually associated with Bible verses.
And so I think the model is kind of like reminded that these almost look like Bible verse markers.
And in a Bible verse setting, 9.11 would come after 9.9.
And so basically the model somehow finds it like cognitively very distracting that in
Bible verses 9.11 would be greater.
Even though here it's actually trying to justify it and come up to the answer with a math,
it still ends up with the wrong answer here.
So it basically just doesn't fully make sense and it's not fully understood and there's
a few jagged issues like that.
So that's why treat this as what it is, which is a stochastic system that is really magical,
but that you can't also fully trust.
And you want to use it as a tool, not as something that you kind of let it rip on a problem
and copy paste the results.
Okay, so we have now covered two major stages of training of large language models.
We saw that in the first stage, this is called the pre-training stage.
We are basically training on internet documents.
And when you train a language model on internet documents, you get what's called a base model.
And it's basically an internet document simulator, right?
Now we saw that this is an interesting artifact
and this takes many months to train on thousands of computers
and it's kind of a lossy compression of the internet
and it's extremely interesting, but it's not directly useful.
Because we don't want to sample internet documents,
we want to ask questions of an AI
and have it respond to our questions.
So for that we need an assistant
and we saw that we can actually construct an assistant
in the process of a post-training and specifically in the process of supervised fine tuning as we
call it. So in this stage, we saw that it's algorithmically identical to pre-training. Nothing
is going to change. The only thing that changes is the data set. So instead of internet documents,
we now want to create and curate a very nice data set of conversations. So we want a million
conversations on all kinds of diverse topics between a human and an assistant and fundamentally
these conversations are created by humans so humans write the prompts and humans write the
ideal responses and they do that based on labeling documentations. Now in the modern stack it's
not actually done fully and manually by humans right they actually now have a lot of help from
these tools so we can use language models to help us create these data sets and we've
just done extensively, but fundamentally it's also coming from human creation at the end.
So we create these conversations that now becomes our data set, we fine tune on it or continue
training on it, and we get an assistant. And then we kind of shift it gears and start
talking about some of the kind of cognitive implications of what this assistant is like.
And we saw that for example the assistant will hallucinate if you don't take some
certain mitigations towards it. So we saw that hallucinations would be common. And then we looked at some
of the mitigations of those hallucinations. And then we saw that the models are quite impressive and
can do a lot of stuff in their head. But we saw that they can also lean on tools to become better.
So for example, we can lean on the web search in order to hallucinate us and to maybe bring up some
more recent information or something like that. Or we can lean on tools like code interpreter.
so the LLM can write some code and actually run it and see the results.
So these are some of the topics we looked at so far.
Now what I'd like to do is I'd like to cover the last and major stage of this pipeline,
and that is reinforcement learning. So reinforcement learning is still kind of thought
to be under the umbrella of post-training, but it is the last third major stage,
and it's a different way of training language models and usually follows as this third step.
So inside companies like OpenAI, you will start here and these are all separate teams, so there's a team doing data for it pre-training and a team doing training for pre-training, and then there's a team doing all the conversation generation in a different team that is doing the supervised fine tuning, and there will be a team for the reinforcement learning as well.
So it's kind of like a handoff of these models. You get your base model, then you find you need to be an assistant, and then you're going to reinforcement learning, which we'll talk about now.
So, that's kind of like the major flow and so, let's now focus on reinforcement learning,
the last major stage of training, and let me first actually motivate it and why we would
want to do reinforcement learning and what it looks like on a high level.
So I would now like to try to motivate the reinforcement learning stage and what it corresponds
to, with something that you're probably familiar with.
And that is basically going to school, so just like you want to school to become really
good at something, we want to take large language models through school.
And really what we're doing is we have a few paradigms of ways of giving them knowledge
or transferring skills.
So in particular, when we're working with textbooks in school, you'll see that there are three
major kind of pieces of information in these textbooks, three classes of information.
The first thing you'll see is you'll see a lot of exposition.
And by the way, this is a totally random book I both from the internet.
I think it's some kind of an organic chemistry or something, I'm not sure.
But the important thing is that you'll see that most of the text, most of it is kind
of just like the meat of it, is exposition.
It's kind of like background knowledge, et cetera.
As you are reading through the words of this exposition, you can think of that roughly
as training on that data.
And that's why when you're reading through this stuff, there's background knowledge and
there's all this context information, it's kind of equivalent to pre-training.
So it's where we build sort of like a knowledge base of this data and get a sense of the topic.
The next major kind of information that you will see is these problems and with their
worked solutions.
So basically a human expert in this case, the author of this book has given us not just
a problem but has also worked through the solution.
And the solution is basically like equivalent to having like this ideal response for an
assistant.
So it's basically the expert is showing us how to solve the problem in its kind of like
in its full form.
So as we are reading the solution, we are basically training on the expert data.
And then later, we can try to imitate the expert.
And basically, that roughly corresponds to having the SFT model.
That's what it would be doing.
So basically, we've already done pre-training, and we've already covered this imitation
of experts and how they solve these problems.
And the third stage of reinforcement learning is basically the practice problems.
So sometimes you'll see this is just a single practice problem here, but of course there
will be usually many practice problems at the end of each chapter in any textbook.
And practice problems of course we know are critical for learning because what are they
getting you to do?
They're getting you to practice to practice yourself and discover ways of solving these
problems yourself.
And so what you get in the practice problem is you get the problem description, but you
are not given the solution, but you are given the final answer, usually in the answer
okay of the textbook. And so you know the final answer that you're trying to get to and you have
the problem statement, but you don't have the solution. You are trying to practice the solution.
You're trying out many different things and you're seeing what gets you to the final solution
the best. And so you're discovering how to solve these problems. So and in the process of that
you're relying on number one, the background information, which comes from pre-training,
and number two, maybe a little bit of imitation of human experts. And you can probably try similar
kinds of solutions and so on. So we've done this and this, and now in this section, we're going to try to practice.
And so we're going to be given prompts, we're going to be given solutions, sorry, the final answers, but we're not going to be given expert solutions.
We have to practice and try stuff out. And that's what reinforcement learning is about.
Okay, so let's go back to the problem that we worked with previously. Just so we have a concrete example to talk through as we explore sort of the topic here.
So, um, I'm here in the Dictoconizer because I'd also like to, well, I get a text box which is useful.
But number two, I want to remind you again that we're always working with one dimensional token sequences.
And so, um, I actually prefer this view because this is like the native view of the LLM of that mixes.
Like, this is what it actually sees. It sees token IDs, right?
Okay.
So, Emily buys three apples and two oranges.
Each orange is $2.
The total cost of all the fruit is $13.
What is the cost of each apple?
And what I'd like you to appreciate here
is these are like four possible candidate solutions
as an example and they all reach the answer three.
Now what I'd like you to appreciate at this point
is that if I'm the human data labeler
that is creating a conversation to be entered into the training set,
I don't actually really know which of these conversations
to add to the data set.
Some of these conversations kind of set up a system of equations, some of them sort of
just talk through it in English, and some of them just kind of like skip right through
to the solution.
If you look at Chachi Bd for example, and you give this question, it defines a system
of variables and it kind of like does this little thing.
We have to appreciate and differentiate between those is, the first purpose of a solution
is to reach the right answer, of course, we want to get the final answer three.
that is the important purpose here.
But there's kind of like a secondary purpose as well,
where here we are also just kind of trying
to make it like nice for the human,
because we're kind of assuming that the person
wants to see this solution,
they want to see the intermediate steps,
we want to present it nicely, et cetera.
So there are two separate things going on here.
Number one is the presentation for the human,
but number two, we're trying to actually get the right answer.
So for the moment, focus on just reaching the final answer.
If we're only care about the final answer,
then which of these is the optimal or like the best prompt,
sorry, the best solution for the LLM to reach the right answer.
And what I'm trying to get at is we don't know.
Me, as a human labeler, I would not
know which one of these is best.
So as an example, we saw earlier on when
we looked at the token sequences here
and the mental arithmetic and reasoning,
we saw that for each token we can only
This meant basically a finite number of, finite amount of compute here.
That is not very large, or you should think about it that way.
And so we can't actually make too big of a leap in any one token, is maybe the way to
think about it.
So as an example in this one, what's really nice about it is that it's very few tokens.
So it's going to take us very short amount of time to get to the answer.
But right here when we're doing 13-4 divide 3 equals, right in this token here, we're
actually asking for a lot of computation to happen on that single individual token.
And so maybe this is a bad example to give to the LLM because it's kind of incentivizing it
to skip through the calculations very quickly and it's going to actually make mistakes and it's
mental arithmetic. So maybe it would work better to spread out more and maybe it would be better
to set up as an equation, maybe it would be better to talk through it. We fundamentally don't know
And we don't know because what is easy for you or I or as human
labelers, what's easy for us or hard for us is different than what's easy or
hard for the LLM. Its cognition is different. And the token sequences are kind
of like different hard for it. And so some of the token sequences here
that are trivial for me might be very too much of a leap for the LLM.
So right here, this token would be way too hard, but conversely, many of the tokens that I'm creating
here might be just trivial to the LLM and we're just wasting tokens like why waste all these tokens
when this is all trivial. So if the only thing we care about is reaching the final answer
and we're separating out the issue of the presentation to the human, then we don't actually really
know how to annotate this example. We don't know what solution to get to the LLM because we are not
the LLM. And it's clear here in the case of like the math example, but this is actually like a very
pervasive issue like for our knowledge is not LLM's knowledge. Like the LLM actually has a ton of
knowledge of PhD in math and physics and chemistry and whatnot. So in many ways it actually knows more
than I do. And I'm potentially not utilizing that knowledge in its problem solving. But conversely,
I might be injecting a bunch of knowledge in my solutions that the LLM doesn't know in its parameters.
And then those are like sudden leaps that are very confusing to the model and so our
cognitions are different and I don't really know what to put here if all we care about
is the reaching the final solution and doing it economically ideally.
And so long story short, we are not in a good position to create these token sequences
for the LLM and they're useful by imitation to initialize the system but we really want
the LLM to discover the token sequences that work for it.
We need to find, it needs to find for itself what token sequence
reliably gets to the answer given the prompt.
And we need to discover that in a process of reinforcement learning
and of trial and error.
So let's see how this example would work like in reinforcement learning.
Okay, so we're now back in the Hugging Face inference playground.
And that just allows me to very easily call different kinds of models.
So as an example here on the top right,
I chose the gem up to 2 billion primary model.
So 2 billion is very, very small.
So this is a tiny model, but it's OK.
So we're going to give it the way that reinforcement learning
will basically work is actually quite simple.
We need to try many different kinds of solutions.
And we want to see which solutions work well or not.
So we're basically going to take the prompt.
We're going to run the model and the model generates a solution.
and then we're gonna inspect the solution.
And we know that the correct answer for this one is $3.
And so indeed, the model gets it correct since it's $3.
So this is correct.
So that's just one attempt at the solution.
So now we're gonna delete this
and we're gonna rerun it again.
Let's try a second attempt.
So the model solves it in a bit slightly different way, right?
Every single attempt will be a different generation
because these models are stochastic systems.
Remember that at every single token here,
we have a probability distribution
and we're sampling from that distribution.
So we end up kind of going down to slightly different paths.
And so this is a second solution
that also ends in the correct answer.
Now we're going to delete that.
Let's go through time.
OK, so again, it's a slightly different solution,
but also gets it correct.
Now we can actually repeat this many times.
And so in practice, you might actually
sample thousands of independent solutions,
or even like million solutions, for just a single prompt.
And some of them will be correct,
and some of them will not be very correct.
And basically, what we want to do is we want to encourage
the solutions that lead to correct answers.
So let's take a look at what that looks like.
So if we come back over here,
here's kind of like a cartoon diagram
of what this is looking like.
We have a prompt,
and then we tried many different solutions in parallel.
And some of the solutions might go well
so they get the right answer, which is in green.
And some of the solutions might go poorly
and may not reach the right answer, which is red.
Now, this problem here unfortunately is not the best example
because it's a trivial prompt.
And as we saw, even like a 2 billion parameter model
always gets it right.
So it's not the best example in that sense.
But let's just exercise some imagination here
and let's just suppose that the green ones are good
and the red ones are bad, OK?
So we generated 15 solutions.
Only four of them got the right answer.
And so now what you want to do is basically
we want to encourage the kinds of solutions that relate to right answers.
So whatever token sequences happened in these red solutions, obviously something went
wrong along the way somewhere.
And this was not a good path to take through the solution.
And whatever token sequences there were in these green solutions, well, things went
pretty well in this situation.
And so we want to do more things like it in prompts like this.
And the way we encourage this kind of behavior in the future is we basically train on these
sequences. But these training sequences now are not coming from expert human
annotators. There's no human who decided that this is the correct solution. This
solution came from the model itself. So the model is practicing here. It's tried
out a few solutions, four of them seem to have worked, and now the model will
kind of like train on them. And this corresponds to a student basically looking
at their solutions and being like, okay, well this one worked really well. So this
is how I should be solving these kinds of problems. And here in this example,
there are many different ways to actually like really tweak the methodology a little bit here,
but just to get the core idea across, maybe it's simplest to just think about
taking the single best solution out of these four, like say this one, that's why it was yellow.
So this is the solution that not only led to the right answer, but maybe had some other
nice properties, maybe it was the shortest one, or it looked nicest in some ways, or
there's other criteria you could think of as an example. But we're going to decide this the top
solution. We're going to train on it. And then the model will be slightly more likely once you do
the parameter update to take this path in this kind of a setting in the future. But you have to
remember that we're going to run many different diverse prompts across lots of math problems and
physics problems and whatever whatever whatever there might be. So tens of thousands of prompts maybe
have in mind there's thousands of solutions per prompt. And so this is all happening kind of like
at the same time. And as we're iterating this process, the model is discovering for itself
what kinds of token sequences lead it to correct answers. It's not coming from a human annotator.
The model is kind of like playing in this playground and it knows what it's trying to get to
and it's discovering sequences that work for it. These are sequences that don't make any mental
leaps, they seem to work reliably and statistically, and fully
utilize the knowledge of the model as it has it. And so this is
the process of reinforcement learning. It's basically a guess
and check, we're going to guess many different types of solutions,
we're going to check them, and we're going to do more of what
worked in the future. And that is reinforcement learning. So in
the context of what came before, we see now that the SFT
model, the supervised fine tuning model, it's still helpful
because it still kind of like initializes the model
a little bit into the vicinity of the correct solutions.
So it's kind of like an initialization of the model.
In the sense that it kind of gets the model to take solutions,
like write out solutions and maybe it has an understanding
of setting up a system of equations
or maybe it kind of like talks through a solution.
So it gets you into the vicinity of correct solutions.
But reinforcement learning is where everything gets dialed in.
We really discover the solutions that work for the model,
get the right answers, we encourage them,
and then the model just kind of gets better over time.
Okay, so that is the high level process
for how we train large language models.
In short, we train them kind of very similar
to how we train children.
And basically, the only difference is that children
go through chapters of books,
and they do all these different types of training exercises,
kind of within the chapter of each book.
But instead when we train AIs,
it's almost like we kind of do it stage by stage,
depending on the type of that stage.
So first, what we do is we do pre-training,
which as we saw as equivalents to basically
reading all the expository material.
So we look at all the textbooks at the same time
and we read all the exposition
and we try to build a knowledge base.
The second thing then is we go into the SFT stage,
which is really looking at all the fixed solutions
from human experts of all the different kinds
of worked solutions across all the textbooks.
And we just kind of get an SFT model
which is able to imitate the experts,
but that's so kind of blindly.
It just kind of like does its best guess,
kind of just like trying to mimic
statistically the expert behavior.
And so that's what you get when you look
at all the work solutions.
And then finally, in the last stage,
we do all the practice problems in the RL stage.
Across all the textbooks, we only do the practice problems.
And that's how we get the RL model.
So on a high level, the way we train LLMS
is very much equivalent to the process that we train,
they were used for training of children.
The next point I would like to make
is that actually these first two stages
pre-training and surprise fine tuning,
they've been around for years
and they are very standard and everyone does them
all the different element providers.
It is this last stage, the RL training
there is a lot more early in its process of development
and is not standard yet in the field.
And so this stage is a lot more kind of early in nascent.
And the reason for that is because I actually skipped
over a ton of little details here in this process.
The high level idea is very simple,
it's trial and error learning,
but there's a ton of details,
a little mathematical kind of like nuances
to exactly how you pick the solutions,
there are the best,
and how much you train on them,
and what is the prompt distribution,
and how to set up the training run,
such that this actually works.
So there's a lot of little details and knobs
to the core idea that is very, very simple.
And so getting the details right here is not trivial.
And so a lot of companies like, for example,
OpenAI and other element providers
have experimented internally with reinforcement learning
fine-tuning for LLM's for a while,
but they've not talked about it publicly.
It's all kind of done inside the company.
And so that's why the paper from DeepSeek
that came out very, very recently was such a big deal
because this is a paper from this company
called DeepSeek AI in China.
And this paper really talked very publicly
about reinforcement learning fine-tuning
for large language models.
And how incredibly important it is
for large language models and how it brings out
a lot of reasoning capabilities in the models
will go into this in a second.
So this paper reinvigorated the public interest
of using RL for LLMS and gave a lot of the
certain degree details there needed to reproduce
the results and actually get the stage to work
for large language models.
So let me take you briefly through this deep seek RLN paper
and what happens when you actually correctly apply RL
to language models and what that looks like
and what that gives you.
So the first thing I'll scroll to is this kind of figure two here, where we are looking
at the improvement in how the models are solving mathematical problems.
So this is the accuracy of solving mathematical problems on the Amy accuracy.
And then we can go to the web page and we can see the kinds of problems that are actually
in these kinds of math problems that are being measured here.
So these are simple math problems you can pause the video if you like, but these are the
kinds of problems that basically the models are being asked to solve.
And you can see that in the beginning they're not doing very well.
But then as you update the model with this many thousands of steps, their accuracy kind
of continues to climb.
So the models are improving and they're solving these problems with a higher accuracy
as you do this trial and error on a large data set of these kinds of problems.
And the models are discovering how to solve math problems.
But even more incredible than the quantitative kind of results of solving these problems
with a higher accuracy is the qualitative means by which the model achieves these results.
So when we scroll down, one of the figures here that is kind of interesting is that later
on in the optimization, the model seems to be using average length per response goes
up.
So the model seems to be using more tokens to get its higher accuracy results.
So it's learning to create very, very long solutions.
Why are these solutions very long?
We can look at them qualitatively here.
So basically what they discover is that the model solution get very, very long partially
because so here's a question and here's kind of the answer from the model.
Well the model learns to do and this is an emergent property of the
optimization. It just discovers that this is good for problem solving
is it starts to do stuff like this. Wait, wait, wait. That's not how a moment I can flag here.
Let's re-evaluate this step by step to identify the correct sum can be.
So what is the model doing here, right? The model is basically re-evaluating steps.
It has learned that it works better for accuracy to try out lots of ideas,
Try something from different perspectives, retrace, reframe, backtrack,
is doing a lot of the things that you and I are doing in a process of problem solving
for mathematical questions. But it's rediscovering what happens in your head,
not what you put down on the solution. And there is no human who can hard-code this stuff
in the ideal assistant response. This is only something that can be discovered in a process
of reinforcement learning because you wouldn't know what to put here. This just turns out to work
for the model and it improves its accuracy in problem solving.
So the model learns what we call these chains of thought in your head
and it's an emergent property of the optimization
and that's what's bloating up the response lens
but that's also what's increasing the accuracy of the problem solving.
So it's incredible here is basically the model is discovering ways to think.
It's learning what I like to call cognitive strategies
of how you manipulate a problem and how you approach it from different perspectives
how you pull in some analogies or do different kinds of things like that,
and how you kind of try out many different things over time,
check a result from different perspectives, and how you kind of solve problems.
But here it's kind of discovered by the RL. So, extremely incredible to see this emerge
in the optimization without having to hard-coded anywhere. The only thing we've given it
are the correct answers, and this comes out from trying to just solve them correctly, which is
incredible. Now let's go back to actually the problem that we've been working with, and let's
Let's take a look at what it would look like for this kind of a model, what we call
reasoning or thinking model, to solve that problem.
Okay, so recall that this is the problem we've been working with.
And when I paste it into the chat GPT 40, I'm getting this kind of a response.
Let's take a look at what happens when you give the same query to what's called a reasoning
or a thinking model.
This is a model that was trained with reinforcement learning.
So this model described in this paper, dpccar1, is available on chat.dpc.com.
So this is kind of like the company that developed it is hosting it.
You have to make sure that the deep think button is turned on to get the R1 model, it's
called.
We can paste it here and run it.
And so let's take a look at what happens now and what is the output of the model.
Okay, so here's what it says.
So this is previously what we get using basically what's an SFT approach, the supervised
find training approach. This is like mimicking an expert solution. This is what we get from
the RL model. Okay, let me try to figure this out. So Emily buys three apples and two oranges.
Each orange costs two dollars, total is 13. I need to find out blah, blah, blah.
So here, as you're reading this, you can't escape thinking that this model is thinking.
It's definitely pursuing the solution. It derives that it must cost three dollars and then it says,
wait a second, let me check my math again to be sure. And then it tries it from a slightly
different perspective. And then it says, yep, all that checks out. I think that's the answer.
I don't see any mistakes. Let me see if there's another way to approach the problem,
maybe setting up an equation. Let's let the cost of one apple be $8, then blah, blah, blah.
Yep, same answer. So definitely each apple is $3. All right, confident that that's correct.
And then what it does, once it sort of did the thinking process, is it writes up the nice solution
for the human. And so this is now considering, so this is more about the correctness aspect,
and this is more about the presentation aspect where it kind of like writes it out nicely
and boxes in the correct answer at the bottom. And so what's incredible about this is we get this
like thinking process at the model. And this is what's coming from the reinforcement learning process.
This is what's bloating up the length of the token sequences. They're doing thinking and they're
trying different ways. This is what's given you higher accuracy and problem solving. And
this is where we are seeing these aha moments and these different strategies and these ideas
for how you can make sure that you're getting the correct answer. The last point I want
to make is some people are a little bit nervous about putting very sensitive data into chat.tipsic.com
because this is a Chinese company so people are a little bit careful and cagey with that a little
bit. DeepSeq R1 is a model that was released by this company. So this is an open source model
or open weights model. It is available for anyone to download and use. You will not be able to
like run it in its full sort of the full model in full precision. You won't run that on a MacBook.
But or like a local device because this is a fairly large model. But many companies are hosting
the full largest model. One of these companies that I like to use is called Together.AI.
So when you go to Together.AI, you sign up and you go to Playgrounds. You can select here
in the chat DeepSeekR1 and there's many different kinds of other models that you can select here.
These are all state-of-the-art models. So this is kind of similar to the hugging-face inference
playground that we've been playing with so far. But Together.AI will usually host all the state
of the art models. So Select DeepSeekR1. You can try to ignore a lot of these. I think the default
I think we'll often be okay and we can put in this and because the model was released by deepseek
what you're getting here should be basically equivalent to what you're getting here. Now because
of the randomness in the sampling we're going to get something slightly different but in principle
this should be identical in terms of the power of the model and you should be able to see the same
things quantitatively and qualitatively but this model is coming from kind of an American company.
So, that's deep seek and that's what's called a reasoning model.
Now, when I go back to chat, let me go to chat here.
Okay, so the models that you're going to see in the drop down here, some of them, like O1, O3 mini, O3 mini high, etc.
They are talking about users advanced reasoning.
Now, what this is referring to, uses advanced reasoning, is it's referring to the fact that it was trained by reinforcement learning
with techniques very similar to those of deep seek R1, per public statements of opening our employees.
any eye employees. So these are thinking models, trained with RL, and these models like
GPT-4O or GPT-4O Mini that you're getting in the free tier, you should think of them
as mostly SFT models, supervised fine tuning models. They don't actually do this like
thinking as you see in the RL models. And even though there's a little bit of reinforcement
learning involved with these models, and I'll go that into that in a second, these are mostly
SFT models, I think you should think about it that way. So in the same way, as what we
we saw here, we can pick one of the thinking models,
like say, O3 mini high.
And these models, by the way,
might not be available to you
unless you pay a charge of the subscription
of either $20 per month or $200 per month
for some of the top models.
So we can pick a thinking model and run.
Now what's gonna happen here is it's gonna say reasoning
and it's gonna start to do stuff like this.
And what we're seeing here is not exactly
the stuff we're seeing here.
So even though under the hood,
the model produces these kinds of chains of thought,
opening our chooses to not show
the exact chains of thought in the web interface.
It shows little summaries of those chains of thought.
And opening our kind of does this,
I think partly because they are worried about
what's called a distillation risk.
That is that someone could come in
and actually try to imitate those reasoning traces
and recover a lot of the reasoning performance
by just imitating the reasoning chains of thought.
And so they kind of hide them,
and they only show little summaries of them.
So you're not getting exactly what you would get
in deep seek as with respect to the reasoning itself.
And then they write up the solution.
So these are kind of like equivalent,
even though we're not seeing the full under the hood details.
Now in terms of the performance,
these models and deep seek models are currently
roughly on par, I would say.
It's kind of hard to tell because of the evaluations.
But if you're paying $200 per month to open AI,
some of these models I believe are currently,
they basically still look better,
but deep seek R1 for now is still a very solid choice
for a thinking model that would be available to you,
sort of either on this website or any other website
because the model has open weights,
you can just download it.
So that's thinking models.
So what is the summary so far?
Well, we've talked about reinforcement learning
and the fact that thinking emerges
in the process of the optimization
on when we basically run RL on many math
and kind of code problems that have verifiable solutions.
So there's like an answer, three, et cetera.
Now, these thinking models, you can access,
and for example, deep seek, or any inference provider
like together.ai and choosing deep seek over there.
These thinking models are also available in chat GPT
under any of the O1 or three models.
But these GPT4O models, et cetera,
they're not thinking models.
You should think of them as mostly SFT models.
Now, if you are, if you have a prompt
that requires advanced reasoning and so on,
you should probably use some of the thinking models
or at least try them out.
But empirically for a lot of my use,
when you're asking a simpler question,
there's like a knowledge-based question or something like that,
this might be overkill.
Like there's no need to think 30 seconds
about some factual question.
So for that, I will sometimes default to just GPT-40.
So empirically, about 80% of my use is just GPT-40.
And when I come across a very difficult problem,
like in math and code, et cetera,
I will reach for the thinking models,
but then I have to wait a bit longer
because they are thinking.
So you can access these on Chatchupity, on DeepSeek.
Also, I wanted to point out that AIStudio.google.com,
even though it looks really busy, really ugly
because Google is just unable to do this kind of stuff
while it's like, what is happening?
But if you choose model and you choose here,
Gemini 2.0 Flash Thinking Experimental 021,
if you choose that one,
That's also a kind of early experiment,
experimental of a thinking model by Google.
So we can go here and we can give it the same problem
and click run.
And this is also a thinking model
that will also do something similar
and comes out with the right answer here.
So basically Gemini also offers a thinking model
and Thropic currently does not offer a thinking model.
But basically, this is kind of like the frontier
of development of these LLMS.
I think RL is kind of like this new exciting stage
but getting the details right is difficult.
And that's why all these models
and thinking models are currently experimental
as of 2025, very early, 2025.
But this is kind of like the frontier development
of pushing the performance in these very difficult problems
using reasoning that is emergent in these optimizations.
One more connection that I wanted to bring up
is that the discovery that reinforcement learning
is extremely powerful way of learning
is not new to the field of AI.
And one place where we've already seen this demonstrated
is in the Game of Go.
And famously, deep mind developed the system AlphaGo,
and you can watch a movie about it,
where the system is learning to play the Game of Go
against top human players.
And when we go to the paper underlying AlphaGo,
so in this paper, when we scroll down,
we actually find a really interesting plot
that I think is kind of familiar to us.
And we're kind of like we discovering
in the more open domain of arbitrary problem solving,
instead of on the close specific domain of the game of Go.
But basically what they saw,
and we're gonna see this in the elements as well,
as this becomes more mature,
is this is the elo rating of playing game of Go,
and this is Lisa Dull, an extremely strong human player.
And here where they are comparing
is this strength of a model learned trained
by supervised learning and a model trained
by reinforcement learning.
So the supervised learning model
is imitating human expert players.
So if you just get a huge amount of games
played by expert players in the game of Go
and you try to imitate them,
you are going to get better, but then you top out.
And you never quite get better
than some of the top, top, top players
in the game of Go, like Lisa though.
So you're never gonna reach there
because you're just imitating human players.
You can't fundamentally go beyond the human player
if you're just imitating human players.
But in a process of reinforcement learning
is significantly more powerful.
In reinforcement learning for a game of go,
it means that the system is playing moves
that empirically and statistically lead to win,
to winning the game.
And so, AlphaGo is a system where it kind of place
against itself.
And it's using reinforcement learning to create a rollouts.
So it's the exact same diagram here.
But there's no prompt, it's just a,
because there's no prompt, it's just a fixed game of go.
But it's trying out lots of solutions,
it's trying out lots of place.
And then the games that leads to a win
instead of a specific answer are reinforced.
They're made stronger.
And so the system is learning basically
the sequences of actions that empirically and statistically
lead to winning the game.
And reinforcement learning is not going
to be constrained by human performance.
And reinforcement learning can do significantly better
and overcome even the top players like Lisa Dull.
And so probably they could have run this longer
and they just chose to crop it at some point
because this costs money.
But this is a very powerful demonstration
of reinforcement learning.
And we're only starting to kind of see hints of this diagram
in larger language models for reasoning problems.
So we're not gonna get too far by just imitating experts.
We need to go beyond that,
set up these little game environments
and let the system discover reasoning traces
or like ways of solving problems that are unique
and that just basically work well.
not on this aspect of uniqueness.
Notice that when you're doing reinforcement learning,
nothing prevents you from veering off the distribution
of how humans are playing the game.
And so when we go back to this AlphaGo search here,
one of the suggested modifications is called move 37.
And move 37 in AlphaGo is referring
to a specific point in time where AlphaGo basically
played a move that no human expert would play.
So the probability of this move to be played
by a human player was evaluated to be about one in 10,000.
So it's a very rare move, but in retrospect,
it was a brilliant move.
So AlphaGo, in the process of reinforcement learning,
discovered kind of like a strategy of playing
that was unknown to humans, but is in retrospect a brilliant.
I recommend this YouTube video.
Lisa Dole versus AlphaGo moved 37 reactions analysis.
And this is kind of what it looked like
when AlphaGo played this move.
value. That's a very surprising move. I thought it was a mistake. When I see this move.
Anyways, so basically people are kind of freaking out because it's a move that a human would
not play, that alpha go played because in its training, this move seemed to be a good idea.
It just happens not to be a kind of thing that a human would do. And so that is, again,
the power of reinforcement learning. And in principle, we can actually see the equivalence of that
if we continue scaling this paradigm in language models and what that looks like is kind of unknown.
So what does it mean to solve problems in such a way that even humans would not be able to get?
How can you be better at reasoning or thinking than humans? How can you go beyond just
thinking human? Like maybe it means discovering analogies that humans would not be able to create
or maybe it's like a new thinking strategy. It's kind of hard to think through. Maybe it's
It's a whole new language that actually is not even English.
Maybe it discovers its own language that is a lot better at thinking because the model
is unconstrained to even stick with English.
So maybe it takes a different language to think in or it discovers its own language.
So in principle, the behavior of the system is a lot less defined.
It is open to do whatever works and it is open to also slowly drift from the distribution
the training data which is English. But all of that can only be done if we have a very large
diverse set of problems in which these strategies can be refined and perfected. And so that is
a lot of the frontier element research that's going on right now is trying to kind of create those
kind of prompt distributions that are large and diverse. These are all kind of like game environments
in which the elements can practice their thinking. And it's kind of like writing these practice
problems, we have to create practice problems for all of domains of knowledge. And if we have
practice problems and tons of them, the models will be able to reinforcement learning,
reinforcement learning on them and kind of create these kinds of diagrams, but in the domain of
open thinking instead of closed domain like Game of Go. There's one more section within reinforcement
learning that I wanted to cover. And that is that of learning in unverifiable domains.
So, so far, all of the problems that we've looked at are in what's called verifiable domains.
That is, any candidate solution, we can score very easily against a concrete answer.
So for example, answer is three, and we can very easily score these solutions against
the answer of three.
Either, we require the models to like box in their answers, and then we just check for
a quality of whatever is in the box with the answer, or we can also use kind of what's
called an LLM judge.
So the LLM judge looks at a solution and it gets the answer
and just basically scores the solution
for whether it's consistent with the answer or not.
And LLMs empirically are good enough at the current capability
that they can do this fairly reliably.
So we can apply those kinds of techniques as well.
In any case, we have a concrete answer
and we're just checking solutions against it
and we can do this automatically
with no kind of humans in the loop.
The problem is that we can't apply this strategy
in what's called unverifiable domains.
So usually these are, for example, creative writing tasks,
like write a joke about pelicans or write a poem
or summarize a paragraph or something like that.
In these kinds of domains, it becomes harder
to score our different solutions to this problem.
So for example, writing a joke about pelicans,
we can generate lots of different jokes, of course,
that's fine.
For example, you can go to Chashy Petey
and we can get it to generate a joke about pelicans.
So much stuff in their beaks
because they don't pelican in backpacks.
Why?
Okay, we can try something else.
White and Pelicans ever pay for their drinks
because they always billet to someone else, ha ha.
Okay, so these models are not obviously
not very good at humor.
Actually, I think it's pretty fascinating
because I think humor is secretly very difficult
and the model doesn't have the capability, I think.
Anyway, in any case, you could imagine creating lots of jokes.
The problem that we are facing is how do we score them?
Now, in principle, we could of course get a human
to look at all these jokes, just like I did right now.
The problem with that is if you are doing
the reinforcement learning,
you're gonna be doing many thousands of updates.
And for each update, you wanna be looking at,
say, thousands of prompts.
And for each prompt, you wanna be potentially looking at,
looking at hundreds or thousands
of different kinds of generations.
And so there's just like way too many of these to look at.
And so, in principle, you could have a human inspect all of them
and score them and decide that, okay, maybe this one is funny.
And maybe this one is funny.
And this one is funny, and we could train on them
to get the model to become slightly better at jokes
in the company's Republicans at least.
The problem is that it's just like way too much human time.
This is an unscable strategy.
We need some kind of an automatic strategy for doing this.
And one sort of solution to this was proposed in this paper
that introduced what's called reinforcement learning
from human feedback.
And so this was a paper from Open AI at the time.
And many of these people are now co-founders and anthropic.
And this kind of proposed a approach
for basically doing reinforcement learning
in unverifiable domains.
So let's take a look at how that works.
So this is the cartoon diagram of the core IDS involved.
So as I mentioned, the naive approach
is if we just set infinity human time,
we could just run RL in these domains just fine.
So for example, we can run RL as usual if I have infinity
units, I just want to do, and these are just cartoon numbers.
I want to do 1,000 updates, where each update will be on 1,000
prompts.
And for each prompt, we're going to have 1,000 rollouts that
we're scoring.
So we can run RL with this kind of a setup.
The problem is, in the process of doing this,
I will need to ask a human to evaluate a joke,
a total of 1 billion times.
And so that's a lot of people looking at really terrible jokes.
So we don't want to do that.
So instead we want to take the RLHF approach.
So in RLHF approach, we are kind of like
that the core trick is that of indirection.
So we're gonna involve humans just a little bit.
And the way we cheat is that we basically train
a whole separate neural network that we call a reward model.
And this neural network will kind of like
imitate human scores.
So we're gonna ask humans to score rollouts.
We're gonna then imitate human scores
using a neural network.
And this neural network will become a kind of simulator
of human preferences.
And now that we have a neural network simulator,
we can do RL against it.
So instead of asking a real human,
we're asking a simulated human
for their score of a joke as an example.
And so once we have a simulator,
we're off to the racist because we can query it
as many times as we want to
and it's a whole automatic process
and we can now do a reinforcement learning
with respect to the simulator.
And the simulator, as we might expect,
is not going to be a perfect human,
but if it's at least statistically similar
to human judgment, then you might expect
that this will do something.
And in practice, indeed, it does.
So once we have a simulator, we can do RL
and everything works great.
So let me show you a cartoon diagram
a little bit of what this process looks like.
Although the details are not 100,
like super important, it's just a core idea
of how this works.
So here I have a cartoon diagram
of a hypothetical example of what training
the reward model would look like.
So we have a prompt, like write a joke about bellicants.
And then here we have five separate roll outs.
So these are all five different jokes,
just like this one.
Now, the first thing we're gonna do
is we are going to ask a human to order these jokes
from the best to worst.
So this is, so here, this human thought
that this joke is the best, the funniest.
So number one, joke.
This is number two joke, number three joke, four and five.
So this is the worst joke.
We're asking humans to order instead of give scores directly
because it's a bit of an easier task.
It's easier for a human to give an ordering
than to give precise scores.
Now, that is not the supervision for the model.
So the human has ordered them
and that is kind of like their contribution
to the training process.
But now separately what we're going to do
is we're going to ask a reward model
about its scoring of these jokes.
Now the reward model is a whole separate neural network,
completely separate neural net,
And it's also probably a transformer,
but it's not a language model in a sense
that it generates diverse language, et cetera.
It's just a scoring model.
So the reward model will take as an input,
the prompt, number one, and number two, a candidate joke.
So those are the two inputs that go into the reward model.
So here, for example, the reward model
we take in this prompt and this joke.
Now, the output of a reward model is a single number.
and this number is thought of as a score,
and it can range, for example, from zero to one.
So zero would be the worst score,
and one would be the best score.
So here are some examples of what a hypothetical reward model
at some stage in the training process
would give as a scoring to these jokes.
So point one is a very low score,
point eight is a really high score, and so on.
And so now we compare the scores given by the reward model
with the ordering given by the human.
And there's a precise mathematical way
to actually calculate this, basically,
set up a loss function and calculate a correspondence here
and update a model based on it.
But I just want to give you the intuition, which
is that as an example here, for this second joke,
the human thought that it was the funniest
and the model kind of agreed, 0.8 is a relatively high score.
But this score should have been even higher.
So after an update, we would expect
that maybe this score should have been,
will actually grow after an update of the network
to be like, say, point eight one or something.
For this one here, they actually are in a massive disagreement
because the human thought that this was number two,
but here the score is only point one.
And so this score needs to be much higher.
So after an update on top of this kind of a supervision,
this might grow a lot more.
Like maybe it's point one five or something like that.
And then here, the human thought that this one
the worst joke but here the model actually gave it a fairly high number so you might expect
that after the update this would come down to maybe 3.5 or something like that. So basically we're
doing what we did before. We're slightly nudging the predictions from the models using neural
network training process and we're trying to make the reward model scores be consistent with human
ordering and so as we update the reward model on human data it becomes better and better
simulator of the scores and orders that humans provide.
And then becomes kind of like the simulator of human preferences, which we can then
do RL against.
But critically, we're not asking humans 1 billion times to look at a joke.
We're maybe looking at a thousand prompts and five or a lot of each.
So maybe 5,000 jokes that humans have to look at in total.
And they just give the ordering and then we're training them out to be consistent with that
ordering.
And I'm skipping over the mathematical details.
But I just want you to understand a high level idea that this reward model is basically
giving us this course, and we have a way of training it to be consistent with human orderings.
And that's how our LHF works.
Okay, so that is the rough idea.
We basically train simulators of humans and RL, through respect to those simulators.
Now, I want to talk about first the upside of reinforcement learning from human feedback.
The first thing is that this allows us to run reinforcement learning, which we know is
incredibly powerful set of techniques, and it allows us to do it in arbitrary domains,
and including the ones that are unverifiable.
So things like summarization and point writing, joke writing, or any other creative writing
really, in domains outside of math and code, etc.
Now empirically what we see when we actually apply RLHF is that this is a way to improve
the performance of the model.
And I have a top answer for why that might be, but I don't actually know that it is
is like super well established, unlike why this is.
You can empirically observe that when you do
RLHF correctly, the models you get
are just like a little bit better.
But as to why is I think like not as clear?
So here's my best guess.
My best guess is that this is possibly mostly
due to the discriminator generator gap.
What that means is that in many cases,
it is significantly easier to discriminate
than to generate for humans.
So in particular, an example of this
is when we do supervised fine tuning, SFT,
we're asking humans to generate the ideal assistant response.
And in many cases here, as I've shown it,
ideal response is very simple to write.
But in many cases, it might not be.
So for example, in summarization or poem writing or joke
writing, how are you as a human labeler
supposed to get the ideal response in these cases?
It requires create a human writing to do that.
And so Arleich have kind of sidesteps this
because we get to ask people a significantly easier question
as a data labelers.
They're not asked to write poems directly.
They're just given five poems from the model
and they're just asked to order them.
And so that's just a much easier task
for a human labeler to do.
And so what I think this allows you to do basically is
it kind of allows a lot more higher accuracy data
because we're not asking people to do the generation task
which can be extremely difficult.
Like we're not asking them to do creative writing,
or just trying to get them to distinguish
between creative writings and find ones that are best.
And that is the signal that humans are providing,
just the ordering.
And that is their input into the system.
And then the system in our LHF just discovers
the kinds of responses that would be graded well by humans.
And so that step of indirection
allows the models to be coming for better.
So that is the upside of RLHF.
It allows us to run RL.
It empirically results in better models.
And it allows people to contribute their supervision
even without having to do extremely difficult tasks,
in the case of writing ideal responses.
Unfortunately, RLHF also comes with significant downsides.
And so the main one is that basically,
we are doing reinforcement learning
not with respect to humans and actual human judgment,
but with respect to a lossy simulation of humans, right?
and this lossy simulation could be misleading
because it's just a simulation, right?
It's just a language model that's kind of outpitting scores
and it might not perfectly reflect
the opinion of an actual human with an actual brain
in all the possible different cases.
So that's number one.
There's actually something even more subtle
and devious going on that really dramatically holds back
our LHF as a technique that we can really scale
to significantly kind of smart systems.
And that is that reinforcement learning
is extremely good at discovering a way
to gain the model, to gain the simulation.
So this reward model that we're constructing here,
that gives the scores.
These models are transformers.
These transformers are massive neural nets.
They have billions of parameters,
and they imitate humans, but they do so
in the kind of like a simulation way.
Now the problem is that these are massive,
complicated systems, right?
There's a billion parameters here
that are outputting a single score.
It turns out that there are ways to gain these models.
You can find kinds of inputs
that were not part of their training set.
And these inputs inexplicably get very high scores,
but in a fake way.
So very often what you find, if you run RLHF for very long,
so for example, if we do 1,000 updates,
which is like, say a lot of updates,
you might expect that your jokes are getting better
and that you're getting real bangers about pelicans,
but that's not exactly what happens.
What happens is that, in the first few hundred steps,
the jokes about Pelicans are probably improving a little bit,
and then they actually dramatically fall off the cliff
and you start to get extremely nonsensical results.
Like, for example, you start to get
the top joke about Pelicans starts to be,
and this makes no sense, right?
Like, when you look at it, why should this be a top joke?
But when you take, and you plug it into your reward model,
you'd expect score of zero,
but actually the reward model loves this as a joke.
it will tell you that the the the the is a score of 1.0.
This is a top joke and this makes no sense, right?
But it's because these models are just simulations of humans
and they're massive neural nets
and you can find inputs at the bottom
that kind of like get into the part of the input space
that kind of gives you non-sensical results.
These examples are what's called adversarial examples
and I'm not gonna go into the topic too much
but these are adversarial inputs to the model.
They are specific little inputs
that kind of go between the nooks and crannies of the model
and give non-sensical results at the top.
Now, here's what you might imagine doing.
You say, okay, that is obviously not score of one.
It's obviously a low score.
So, let's add it to the dataset
and give it an ordering that is extremely bad
like a score of five.
And, indeed, your model will learn
that that that that should have a very low score
and it will give it score of zero.
The problem is that there will always be
basically infinite number of non-sensical adversarial examples
hiding in the model.
If you iterate this process many times
and you keep adding non-sensical stuff to your reward model
and giving it very low scores, you'll never win the game.
You can do this many, many rounds
and reinforcement learning, if you run it long enough,
will always find a way to gain the model.
It will discover adversarial examples.
It will get really high scores with non-sensical results.
And fundamentally, this is because our scoring function
is a giant neural nut and RL is extremely good at finding just the ways to trick it.
So long story short, you always run RLHF for maybe a few hundred updates,
the models getting better, and then you have to crop it and you are done.
You can't run too much against this reward model because the optimization will start to gain it
it and you basically crop it and you call it and you ship it and you can improve the
reward model but you kind of like come across these situations eventually at some point.
So RLHF basically what I usually say is that RLHF is not RL and what I mean by that is
I mean RLHF is RL obviously but it's not RL in the magical sense.
This is not RL that you can run indefinitely.
These kinds of problems, like where you are getting concrete correct answer, you cannot
gain this as easily.
You either get the correct answer you didn't, and the scoring function is much, much simpler.
You're just looking at the boxed area and seeing if the result is correct.
So it's very difficult to gain these functions, but gaming a reward model is possible.
Now in these very five domains, you can run RL indefinitely.
You could run for tens of thousands, hundreds of thousands of steps and discover all kinds
a really crazy strategies that we might not even ever think about of performing really
well for all these problems. In the game of Go, there's no way to beat, to basically
game the winning of a game, or losing of a game. With a perfect simulator, we know all
the different, where all the stones are placed, and we can calculate whether someone has
one or not. There's no way to game that. And so you can do RL indefinitely, and you
can eventually beat even at least a dough.
But with models like this, which are gameable,
you cannot repeat this process indefinitely.
So I kind of see RLHF as not real RL
because the reward function is gameable.
So it's kind of more like in the realm
of like little fine tuning.
It's a little improvement, but it's not something
that is fundamentally set up correctly,
where you can insert more compute, run for longer,
and get much better and magical results.
So it's not RL in that sense.
It's not RL in the sense that it lacks magic.
It can fine tune your model and get a better performance.
And indeed, if we go back to chassis PT,
the GPT-40 model has gone through RLHF
because it works well.
But it's just not RL in the same sense.
RLHF is like a little fine tune
that slightly improves your model.
It's maybe like the way I would think about it.
OK, so that's most of the technical content
that I wanted to cover.
I took you through the three major stages
paradigms of training these models. Pre-training, supervised fine training, and reinforcement learning,
and I showed you that they loosely respond to the process we already use for teaching children.
And so in particular we talked about pre-training being sort of like the basic knowledge acquisition
of reading exposition, supervised fine training being the process of looking at lots and lots of
worked examples and imitating experts, and practice problems. The only difference is that we now
have to effectively write textbooks for LLMs and AI's across all the disciplines of human knowledge
and also in all the cases where we actually would like them to work like code and math and
you know basically all the other disciplines. So in the process of writing textbooks for them,
refining all the algorithms that I've presented on the high level and then of course doing a
really really good job at the execution of training these models at scale and efficiently.
So in particular I didn't go into too many details but these are extremely
large, uncomplicated distributed sort of jobs that have to run over tens of thousands or even
hundreds of thousands of GPUs. And the engineering that goes into this is really at the state of
the art of what's possible with computers at that scale. So I didn't cover that aspect too much, but
this is a very kind of serious and they were underlying all these very simple algorithms
ultimately. Now I also talked about sort of like the theory of mine a little bit of these models,
And the thing I want you to take away is that these models are really good, but they're extremely useful as tools for your work.
You shouldn't trust them fully, and I showed you some examples of that.
Even though we have mitigations for hallucinations, the models are not perfect, and they will hallucinate still.
It's gotten better over time, and it will continue to get better, but they can hallucinate.
In addition to that, I covered what I call the Swiss cheese model of Ellen capabilities that you should have in your mind.
The models are incredibly good across so many different disciplines, but then fail randomly
almost in some unique cases.
So for example, what is bigger 9.11 or 9.9, like the model doesn't know, but simultaneously,
it can turn around and solve all impiate questions.
And so this is a hole in the Swiss cheese, and there are many of them, and you don't want
to trick over them.
So don't treat these models as infallible models, check their work, use them as tools, use
them for inspiration, use them for the first draft, but work with them as tools, and
be ultimately responsible for the product of your work.
And that's roughly what I wanted to talk about.
This is how they're trained, and this is what they are.
Let's not turn to what are some of the future capabilities of these models, probably what's
coming down the pipe.
And also, where can you find these models?
I have a few bullet points on some of the things that you can expect coming down the pipe.
The first thing you'll notice is that the models will very rapidly become multimodal.
Everything I've talked about above, concerned text, but very soon we'll have all of them
that can not just handle text, but they can also operate natively and very easily over
audio, so they can hear and speak, and also images, so they can see and paint.
And we're already seeing the beginnings of all of this, but this will be all done natively
inside the language model, and this will enable kind of like natural conversations.
And roughly speaking, the reason that this is actually no different from everything we've
covered above is that, as a baseline, you can tokenize audio and images and apply the
exact same approaches of everything that we've talked about above.
So it's not a fundamental change, it's just we have to add some tokens.
So as an example, for tokenizing audio, we can look at slices of the spectrogram of the
audio signal, and we can tokenize that and just add more tokens that suddenly represent
audio and just add them into the context windows and train on them just like
about. The same for images we can use patches and we can separately tokenize
patches and then what is an image in images just a sequence of tokens and this
actually kind of works and there's a lot of early work in this direction and so
we can just create streams of tokens there are representing audio images as
well as text and interspersed them and handled them all simultaneously in a
single model. So that's one example of multi-modality. Second something that
people are very interested in is currently most of the work is that we're handing
individual tasks to the models on kind of like a silver platter. Like please
solve this task for me and the model sort of like does this little task. But it's
up to us to still sort of like organize a coherent execution of tasks to
perform jobs. And the models are not yet at the capability required to do this
in a coherent error correcting way over long periods of time. So they're not
able to fully shrink together tasks to perform these longer learning jobs. But they're getting there
and this is improving over time. But probably what's going to happen here is we're going to start
to see what's called agents which perform tasks over time and you supervise them and you watch
their work and they come up to once in a while report progress and so on. So we're going to see more
longer running agents tasks that don't just take you know a few seconds of response but many tens of
of seconds or even minutes or hours over time.
But these models are not invaluable as we talked about
above, so all this will require supervision.
So for example, in factories, people
talk about the human-to-robot ratio for automation.
I think we're going to see something
similar in the digital space, where we are going
to be talking about human-to-agent ratios,
where humans becomes a lot more supervisors of egyptic tasks
in the digital domain.
Next, I think everything is going
to become a lot more pervasive and invisible.
So it's kind of like integrated into the tools
and everywhere and in addition,
kind of like computer using.
So right now these models aren't able to take actions
on your behalf, but I think this is a separate bullet point.
If you saw Chashiviti launch the operator,
then that's one early example of that
where you can actually hand off control to the model
to perform keyboard and mouse actions on your behalf.
So that's also something that I think is very interesting.
The last point I have here is just a general comment
that there's still a lot of research
to potentially do in this domain.
One example of that is something along the lines
of test time training.
So remember that everything we've done above
and that we talked about has two major stages.
There's first the training stage
where we tune the parameters of the model
to perform the tasks well.
Once we get the parameters, we fix them
and then we deploy the model for inference.
From there, the model is fixed.
It doesn't change anymore.
It doesn't learn from all the stuff
that it's doing a test time.
It's a fixed number of parameters.
And the only thing that is changing
is now the tokens inside the context windows.
And so the only type of learning, or test time
learning that the model has access to,
is the in-context learning of it's kind of like
dynamically adjustable context window,
depending on what it's doing at test time.
So, but I think this is still different from humans
who actually are able to actually learn
depending on what they're doing,
especially when you sleep, for example,
like your brain is updating your parameters
or something like that, right?
So there's no kind of equivalent of that
currently in these models and tools.
So there's a lot of like more wonky ideas,
I think, that are to be explored still.
And in particular, I think this will be necessary
because the context window is a finite and precious resource.
And especially once we start to tackle
very long running multimodal tasks
and we're putting in videos and these token windows
will basically start to grow extremely large,
like not thousands or even hundreds of thousands,
but significantly beyond that.
And the only trick we have available to us right now
is to make the context Windows longer.
But I think that that approach by itself
will not scale to actual long running tasks
that are multimodal over time.
And so I think new ideas are needed
in some of those disciplines and some of those kind of cases
in the maze where these tasks are going
to require very long contexts.
So those are some examples of some of the things
you can expect coming down the pipe.
Let's not turn to where you can actually kind of keep track
this progress and, you know, be to date with the latest
and greatest of what's happening in the field.
So I would say the three resources that I have consistently
used to stay up to date are number one,
alumarina, so let me show you alumarina.
This is basically an alum leader board
and it ranks all the top models
and the ranking is based on human comparisons.
So humans prompt these models
and they get to judge which one gives a better answer.
They don't know which model is which,
they're just looking at which models the better answer.
And you can calculate a ranking,
and then you get some results.
And so what you can see here is the different organizations,
like Google Gemini, for example, that produced these models.
When you click on any one of these,
it takes you to the place where that model is hosted.
And then here we see Google is currently on top
with OpenAI right behind.
Here we see DeepSeek in position number three.
Now the reason this is a big deal
is the last column here.
You see a license.
deep seek is an MIT licensed model.
It's open weights.
Anyone can use these weights.
Anyone can download them.
Anyone can host their own version of deep seek.
And they can use it in whatever way they like.
And so it's not a proprietary model
that you don't have access to.
It's basically an open weights release.
And so this is kind of unprecedented
that a model this strong was released with open weights.
So pretty cool from the team.
Next up, we have a few more models from Google and OpenAI.
And then when you continue to scroll down,
you're still just see some other usual suspects.
So XAI here andthropic was on it here at number 14
and then meta with Lama over here.
So Lama similar to DeepSeek is an open weights model
and so but it's down here as opposed to up here.
Now I will say that this leaderboard was really good
for a long time.
I do think that in the last few months
become a little bit gained, and I don't trust it as much as I used to. I think just empirically,
I feel like a lot of people, for example, are using Sonnet from Anthropic and that it's a really
good model, but that's all the way down here in number 14. Conversely, I think not as many people
are using Gemini, but it's actually really, really high. I think use this as a first pass,
But sort of try out a few of the models for your tasks and see which one performs better.
The second thing that I would point to is the AI News Letter.
So AI News is not very creatively named, but it is a very good newsletter produced by Swix and Friends.
So thank you for maintaining it.
And it's been very helpful to me because it is extremely comprehensive.
So if you go to Archives, you see that it's produced almost every other day.
day. And it is very comprehensive and some of it is written by humans and curated by humans,
but a lot of it is constructed automatically with all elements. So you'll see that it's
very comprehensive and you're probably not missing anything major if you go through it.
Of course, you're probably not going to go through it. This is so long, but I do think that
these summaries all the way up top are quite good and I think have some human oversight.
So this has been very helpful to me. And the last thing I would point to is just X and Twitter. A lot
of AI happens on X. And so I would just follow people who you like and trust and get all your
latest and greatest on X at all. So these are the major places that have worked from me over time.
And finally, a few words on where you can find the models and where can you use them.
So the first one I would say is for any of the biggest proprietary models, you just have to go
to the website of that Ellen provider. So for example, for OpenAI, that's chat.com. I believe
actually works now. So that's for OpenAI. Now for Gemini, I think it's Gemini.google.com
or AI Studio. I think they have two for some reason that I didn't fully understand. No one does.
For the OpenWaitz models, like deep-sea, Klamac, etc., you have to go to some kind of an inference
provider available on them. So my favorite one is to be together.ai, and I'll show you that when you go
to the playground of together.ai, then you can sort of pick lots of different models, and all of these
These are open models of different types, and you can talk to them here as an example.
Now if you'd like to use a base model, like a base model, then this is where I think
it's not as common to find base models, even on these inference providers.
They are all targeting assistants and chat, and so I think even here I can't see base models
here.
So for base models, I usually go to a hyperbolic, because they serve my Lama 3.1 base,
and I love that model, and you can just talk to it here.
So as far as I know, this is a good place for a base model and I wish more people hosted
base models because they are useful and interesting to work with in some cases.
Finally, you can also take some of the models that are smaller and you can run them locally.
And so, for example, deep seek of the biggest model, you're not going to be able to run
locally on your MacBook, but there are smaller versions of the deep seek model that are what's
called distilled.
And then also you can run these models at smaller precision, so not at the native precision
you know, for example, FP8 on Deepseek or, you know, BF16 Lama, but much, much lower than
that. And don't worry if you don't fully understand those details, but you can run smaller versions
that have been distilled and that have even lower precision, and then you can fit them on
your computer. And so you can actually run pretty okay models on your laptop. And my favorite
I think place I go to usually is Alam Studio, which is basically an app you can get. And
I think it kind of actually looks really ugly and it's,
I don't like that it shows you all these models
that are basically not that useful.
Like everyone just wants to run deep seek.
So I don't know why they give you
these 500 different types of models.
They're really complicated to search for
and you have to choose different installations
and different decisions and it's all really confusing.
But once you actually understand how it works
and that's a whole separate video,
then you can actually load up the model.
Like here I loaded up a Lama 3.2 instruct 1 billion.
And you can just talk to it.
So I ask for pelican jokes and I can ask for another one and it gives me another one,
etc.
All of this that happens here is locally on your computer.
So we're not actually going to anywhere else.
This is running on the GPU on the MacBook Pro.
So that's very nice.
And you can then eject the model when you're done and that frees up the RAM.
So LM Studio is probably like my favorite one, even though I don't, I think it's got a
lot of UI UX issues and it's really geared towards professionals almost.
But if you watch some videos on YouTube, I think you can figure out how to use this interface.
So those are a few words on where to find them.
So let me now loop back around to where we started.
The question was when we go to chashypt.com and we enter some kind of a query.
And we hit go.
What exactly is happening here?
What are we seeing?
What are we talking to?
How does this work?
And I hope that this video gave you some appreciation for some of the under the hood
of details of how these models are trained
and what this is that is coming back.
So in particular, we now know that your query is taken
and is first chopped up into tokens.
So we go to tokenizer.
And here is the place in the format
that is for the user query.
We basically put in our query right there.
So our query goes into what we discussed here
is the conversation protocol format, which
is this way that we maintain conversation objects.
So this gets inserted there.
And then this whole thing ends up
being just a token sequence, a one-dimensional token
sequence under the hood.
So ChachiPT saw this token sequence.
And then when we had to go, it basically
continues appending tokens into this list.
It continues the sequence.
It acts like a token autocomplete.
So in particular, it gave us this response.
So we can basically just put it here
and we see the tokens that it continued.
these are the tokens that are continued with roughly.
Now the question becomes, okay,
why are these the tokens that the model responded with?
What are these tokens?
Where are they coming from?
What are we talking to?
And how do we program this system?
And so that's where we shifted gears
and we talked about the under the pieces of it.
So the first stage of this process,
and there are three stages, is the pre-training stage,
which fundamentally has to do with just knowledge acquisition
from the internet into the parameters
of this neural network.
And so the neural net internalizes a lot of knowledge
from the internet.
But where the personality really comes in
is in the process of supervised pioneering here.
And so what happens here is that basically the company,
like OpenAI, will curate a large data set of conversations,
like, say, 1 million conversation across very diverse topics.
And they will be conversations between a human
and an assistant.
And even though there's a lot of synthetic data generation
used throughout this entire process
and a lot of LLM help and so on.
Fundamentally, this is a human data curation task
with lots of humans involved.
And in particular, these humans are data laborers,
hired by OpenAI, who are given labeling instructions
that they learn, and their task is to create ideal
assistant responses for any arbitrary prompts.
So they are teaching the neural network
by example how to respond to prompts.
So what is the way to think about what came back here?
like what is this?
Well, I think the right way to think about it
is that this is the neural network simulation
of a data labeler at OpenAI.
So it's as if I gave this query to a data labeler OpenAI
and this data labeler first reads all the labelling
instructions from OpenAI and then spends two hours
writing up the ideal assistant response to this query
and giving it to me.
Now, we're not actually doing that, right?
Because we didn't wait two hours.
So what we're getting here is a neural network simulation
of that process.
And we have to keep in mind that these neural networks
don't function like human brains do.
They are different.
What's easy or hard for them is different
from what's easy or hard for humans.
And so we really are just getting a simulation.
So here I show you this is a token stream
and this is fundamentally the neural network
with a bunch of activations and neurons in between.
This is a fixed mathematical expression
that mixes inputs from tokens
with parameters of the model and they get mixed up
and get you the next token in a sequence.
But this is a finite amount of compute
that happens for every single token.
And so this is some kind of a lossy simulation
of a human that is kind of like restricted in this way.
And so whatever the humans write,
the language model is kind of imitating
on this token level with only this specific computation
for every single token in a sequence.
We also saw that as a result of this and the cognitive differences, the models will suffer
in a variety of ways.
And you have to be very careful with their use.
So for example, we saw that they will suffer from hallucinations.
And they also, we have the sense of a Swiss cheese modeled all in capabilities where basically
there's like holes in the cheese.
Sometimes the models will just arbitrarily do something dumb.
So even though they're doing lots of magical stuff, sometimes they just can't.
So maybe you're not giving them enough tokens to think and maybe they're going to just
make stuff up because they're mental arithmetic breaks.
Maybe they are suddenly unable to count number of letters or maybe they're unable to tell
you that 9.11 is smaller than 9.9 and it looks kind of dumb.
And so it's a Swiss cheese capability and we have to be careful with that.
And we saw the reasons for that.
But fundamentally, this is how we think of what came back.
Again, simulation of this neural network of a human data
labeler following the labelling instructions at OpenAI.
So that's what we're getting back.
Now, I do think that the things change a little bit
when you actually go and reach for one of the thinking
models, like O3, many high.
And the reason for that is that GPT4O basically
doesn't do reinforcement learning.
It does do RLHF, but I've told you that RLHF is not RL.
There's no time for magic in there.
It's just a little bit of a fine tuning
is the way to look at it.
But these thinking models, they do use RL.
So they go through this third stage
of perfecting their thinking process
and discovering new thinking strategies
and solutions to problem solving
that look a little bit like your internal monologue
in your head.
and they practice that on a large collection of practice problems
that companies like OpenAI create and curate
and then make available to the alums.
So when I come here and I talk to a thinking model
and I put in this question,
what we're seeing here is not anymore just the straightforward simulation
of a human data labeler.
Like this is actually kind of new, unique, and interesting.
And of course, OpenAI is not showing us the under-dehood thinking
and the chains of thought that are underlying the reasoning here.
But we know that such a thing exists,
and this is a summary of it.
And what we're getting here is actually not just
an imitation of a human data labeler,
it's actually something that is kind of new and interesting
and exciting in the sense that it is a function of thinking
that was emergent in a simulation.
It's not just imitating human data labeler.
It comes from this reinforcement learning process.
And so here we're of course not giving it a chance
to shine because this is not a mathematical or reasoning
problem.
This is just some kind of a sort of creative writing
problem, roughly speaking.
And I think it's a question and open question
as to whether the thinking strategies
that are developed inside verifiable domains
transfer and are generalizable to other domains
that are unverifiable, such as create writing.
The extent to which that transfer happens
is unknown in the field, I would say.
So we're not sure if we are able to do RL
on everything that is verifiable
and see the benefits of that
on things that are unverifiable like this prompt.
So that's an open question.
The other thing that's interesting
is that this reinforcement learning here
is still like way too new, primal, real, and nascent.
So we're just seeing the beginnings
of the hints of greatness in the reasoning problems.
We're seeing something that is
in principle capable of something like
the equivalent of move 37,
but not in the game of go,
but in open domain thinking and problem solving.
In principle, this paradigm is capable
of doing something really cool, new, and exciting,
something even that no human has thought of before.
In principle, these models are capable of analogies
no human has had.
So I think it's incredibly exciting that these models exist,
but again, it's very early
and these are primal-real models for now.
And they will mostly shine in domains that are very
fiable, like math and code, et cetera.
So very interesting to play with and think about in use.
And then that's roughly it.
I would say those are the broad strokes
of what's available right now.
I will say that overall, it is an extremely exciting time
to be in the field.
Personally, I use these models all the time daily,
tens or hundreds of times, because they dramatically
accelerate my work.
I think a lot of people see the same thing.
I think we're going to see a huge amount of wealth creation
as a result of these models.
Be aware of some of their shortcomings.
Even with RL models, they're going to suffer from some of these.
Use it as a tool in a toolbox.
Don't trust it fully because they will randomly
do dumb things, they will randomly hallucinate, they will randomly skip over some mental arithmetic
and not get it right, they randomly can't count or something like that.
So use them as tools in the toolbox, check their work and own the product of your work,
but use them for inspiration, for first draft, ask them questions, but always check and
verify and you will be very successful in your work if you do so.
So I hope this video was useful and interesting to you, I hope you had fun and it's already
I'm glad very long, so I apologize for that, but I hope it was useful, and yeah, I will
see you later.